
A confirmation and discovery of witchcraft 163Kb
A CONFIRMATION And Discovery of <LOCATION>WITCH-CRAFT</LOCATION>,

Containing these severall particulars;

That there are VVitches called bad Witches, and <PERSON>Witches</PERSON> untruely called good or white Witches, and what manner of people they be, and how they may bee knowne, with many particulars thereunto tending.

Together with the Confessions of many of those executed since May 1645. in the severall Counties hereafter mentioned. As also some objections Answered.

By <PERSON>Iohn Stearne</PERSON>, now of <LOCATION>Lawshall</LOCATION> neere <ORGANIZATION>Burie</ORGANIZATION> Saint <PERSON>Edmonds</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, sometimes of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>.


PROV. 17. 15.

He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, even they both are an abomination to the Lord.

DEVT. 13. 14.

Thou shalt therefore inquire, and make search, and aske diligently, whether it be truth, and the thing certaine.
<LOCATION>LONDON</LOCATION>, Printed by <PERSON>William Wilson</PERSON>, dwelling in <LOCATION>Little Saint Bartholo</LOCATION>|mewes neere <ORGANIZATION>Smithfield</ORGANIZATION>. 1648




<LOCATION>Courteous READER</LOCATION>,

TO the end I might satisfie the opinions of such as desire to be further satisfied concerning the dia|bolicall art, or crying sin, of Witch-craft (as I may so call it;) For the sinne of <MISC>Witch-craft</MISC>, and the diabolical practise thereof, is omnium scelerum atrocissi|mum, and in such as have the knowledge of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, the greatest <PERSON>Apostacie</PERSON> from the faith; for they renounce <PERSON>God</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and give themselves by a covenant to the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, the utter e|nemy to <PERSON>God</PERSON> and all mankind, for in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10, 11, 12. <PERSON>God</PERSON> gave command to all the children of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> that none amongst his should bee such. For those abominations were the children of <LOCATION>Canaan</LOCATION> driven out from before them, and utterly destroyed and plagued. As also <PERSON>Manasseth</PERSON>, 2 <PERSON>Cron</PERSON>. 33. 6. which wickednesse of his was so abhorred of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, as in his dis|pleasure hee mentions it many yeares after by <PERSON>Ieremy</PERSON>, as cause of removing the <LOCATION>Iewes</LOCATION> from their land, and so leading them a|way captive into a strange land, <LOCATION>Ier</LOCATION>. 15. 4, 5. <ORGANIZATION>Idola</ORGANIZATION>|ters ought to dye, as in <LOCATION>Exod</LOCATION>. 22. 20. and 32. 28, 29. Nay in|ticers to <LOCATION>Idolatrie</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Deut</PERSON>. 13. 9. because they worship <PERSON>Devills</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Psal</ORGANIZATION>. 106. 37. 1 Cor. 10. 20. <ORGANIZATION>Revel</ORGANIZATION>. 9. 20. But Witches wor|ship <PERSON>Devills</PERSON>, they invocate them, crave helpe of them, worke by them, and doe them homage, sacrifice to them, and they do it not to stockes and stones, and so mediately to the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION>, as other Idolaters doe, but immediately to the <MISC>Devill</MISC> himselfe, and therefore the greatest Idolaters that can be; and are not they then more worthy of death? And to convince others who are of such an erroneus opinion as to say, notwithstan|ding <MISC>Gods</MISC> law against them, and the holy <MISC>Scripture</MISC> speaking of them, besides the lawes of <MISC>Nations</MISC>, both heathen and <PERSON>Chri</PERSON>|an, made to punish them, that there are no witches, but that there are many poore silly ignorant people hanged wrongfully, and that those who have gone or beene instruments in finding out or discovering those of late made knowne have done it for there owne private ends, for gaine and such like, favouring some where they thought good, and unjustly prosecuting o|thers; I therefore (as my leasure hath permitted me) have given my selfe to the reading of some approved relations touching the arraignement and condemnation of Witches; As also treatises of learned men concerning the devilish art of Witch-craft; adding withall some few things which other|wise I have learned and observed since the 25. of March 1645 as being in part an agent in finding out or discovering some of those since that time, being about two hundred in number, in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Suffolke</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Northamptonshire</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Huntingtonshire</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Bedfordshire</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Norfolke</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cambridgeshire</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Isle of Ely</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>County of Cambridge</LOCATION>, besides other places, just|ly and deservedly executed upon their legall tryalls. Now the occasion being thus offered, and <PERSON>Master Hopkins</PERSON> dead, I de|sire to give some satisfaction to the world, that it may ap|peare, what hath beene done, hath beene for the good of the common wealth, and we free from those aspersions cast upon us, and that I never favored any, or unjustly prosecuted o|thers, but that all that be guilty of this, ought to die; as well the good or white witches so called, as the other: and that there is, and hath beene more favour shewed or at least lesse care taken for the discovery of such as be guilty, then by the word of <PERSON>God</PERSON> there ought. For how many are there now a daies which could be contented to passe by many of them, as <MISC>Magicians</MISC>, <MISC>Negro</MISC>|mancers and such like? of whom his late Majesty of famous renowne in his <PERSON>Demonologie</PERSON> giveth a dreadfull censure, who saith they are to be dealt withall, as with <PERSON>Socerers</PERSON>, and e|specially the curing witch, commonly called the good witch. Nay these rather get credit and estimation, love and liking, as did the <MISC>Magicians</MISC> and Sorcerers with <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Exod</PERSON>. 7. 8. with <PERSON>Nabuchadnezer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Belshazzar</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 47. 12. <ORGANIZATION>Ezek</ORGANIZATION>. 22. As did also <PERSON>Simon Magus</PERSON> with the <MISC>Samaritans</MISC>, who was held to be the great power of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, Acts 8. <ORGANIZATION>Likewise Elimas</ORGANIZATION> with <PERSON>Sergius Paulus</PERSON>, Acts 13. And the <PERSON>Pythonesse</PERSON> with her Ma|ster, Acts 16. And will not many say, surely they worke by <PERSON>God</PERSON>, because they use good prayers and good words, and often name <PERSON>God</PERSON>? but let those remember that the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> himselfe can use good words, Mar. 1. 24. and 5. 7. Acts 17. that hee can counterfeit the habit and words of an holy man, <LOCATION>Sa</LOCATION>|muel. 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. 13, 15, 17. that hee can turne himselfe into an <PERSON>Angell</PERSON> of light, 2 Cor. 11. Therefore hee not teach his servants to feigne holinesse and yet be these in many respects worse then the others, and the holy <MISC>Scripture</MISC> exempts none, but utterly forbids any going to them, or asking counsell of them. I hope this my labour will excuse mee, and give some better satisfaction to those who are not yet fully satisfied herein, for that I shall make it plainely appeare, that I neither formerly, in any of my proceedings concerning this matter, or in penning of this, ayme at mine owne private ends rather then the publique good, for that I shall discover, so far forth as I am able, or at least, as civility and modestie shall give way; yet I am not ignorant how dangerous it is for me to put my selfe so farre forth into the Sea of common opinion, and I cannot see that by reason of the shelves and rocks of injurious conceits which are ready to be found on every hand I am like to passe any adventure; having had experience already how forward many bee in taking part with many of those who have been detected to promote them forward to take the least advantage by suit of law, thereby to aquitt themselves, when as many times it hath fallen out otherwise, and been a meanes to bring to their deserved punishment, but let such remember, the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> needs no provoker. And though <PERSON>Balack</PERSON> sent to <PERSON>Balaam</PERSON> to pursue the people, yet we find the contrary, for surely said <PERSON>Balaam</PERSON>, there is no enchantment in <LOCATION>Iacob</LOCATION>, nor divination against <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>. And yet neverthelesse craving pardon if in any thing herein I have taken too much upon me, I have once ventured to commit my selfe to thy sen|sure, & doubt not of prosperous acceptance, if but a charitable construction be had of my true intent & meaning therein, as from a plaine country man, who intend not to pen any thing but what I shall be able to make appeare plainely to bee truth, and then I shall reckon it as a sufficient recompence for my labour and paines. And so with my due respects I take leave.


<PERSON>JOHN STEARNE</PERSON>. 



A CONFIRMATION and Discovery of WITCHCRAFT.

MAn being borne in sinne, hath thereby since the fall of our first parents lost the <ORGANIZATION>Image of God</ORGANIZATION> in which he was created, through the tempta|tion of <LOCATION>Satan</LOCATION>, and is naturally, wholy pollu|ted with sinne and corruption, whereby he is become of very neere kin unto the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, even his owne child, 1 <ORGANIZATION>Iohn</ORGANIZATION> 3. 10. And that beeing his child, he will doe the Iusts of his Father, <ORGANIZATION>Iohn</ORGANIZATION> 8. 44. and that no doubt in one thing as well as in another, for men love darkenesse more than light, <ORGANIZATION>Iohn</ORGANIZATION> 3. 19. <LOCATION>Yea</LOCATION>, and naturally are given to worke all uncleannesse even with greedinesse, so capti|vated are they to their lusts, <PERSON>Ephes</PERSON>. 4, 19. For <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> hath his wiles, <PERSON>Ephes</PERSON>. 11. his devices, 2 Cor. 2. 11. his depths and policies. <ORGANIZATION>Revel</ORGANIZATION>. 2. 24. his snares to catch people at unawares. 1 <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>. 3. 7. 2 <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>. 2. 26. And being thus furnished, hee dare set upon any, yea upon our <PERSON>Saviour Christ</PERSON> himselfe, to solicit him, yea, and to a most execrable impiety, even to have <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> to fall downe and to worship him a <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, Mat. 4. for he watcheth opportunities, he seeketh occasions, and the least offer he espieth and quickly taketh the same, and so prevaileth often, not only with the rude and sottish, but with the greatest spirits and sharpest witts many times. For man beeing given over to his unruly passion, is violent, inconsiderate and vehement|ly greedy to have his desired ends, by what meanes soever he can at|taine them; which maketh him seeke meanes of the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> to be|come injoyer of his inordinate desires, regarding more the ha|ving of his present will, than respecting his future state af|ter death, and is more taken up to obtaine what he liketh for the bo|dy 2 and outward estate in this world, than with the care of his spiri|tuall condition and estate before <PERSON>God</PERSON> in the world to come, which the naturall man very little or nothing at all regardeth. This be|ing the condition of a naturall man who remaines still unregenerate and given over of <PERSON>God</PERSON> unto <MISC>Satans</MISC> temptation in this kind, how can they resist? Man is weake, <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> is strong, and withall subtill to beguile, they may easily yeeld, for that he hath over meere natu|rall men a ruling power, <ORGANIZATION>Ephes</ORGANIZATION>. 2. 2. who are already in his snare, and at his owne will are taken captive, 2 <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>. 2. 26.

Here some will say, you goe about to make all subject to Witch|craft, or at least all unregenerate persons.

I answer, it said in <ORGANIZATION>Iohn</ORGANIZATION> 3. 6. That which is borne of the flesh is flesh, and that which is borne of the spirit is spirit: and therefore <MISC>Witch-craft</MISC> being as Saint <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> saith, Amongst the fruits of the flesh, <LOCATION>Gal</LOCATION>. 5. 20. one may fall into this sinne aswell as into any other, if <PERSON>God</PERSON> prevent it not. Wherefore it behooves man (if he would pre|vent the power of the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION> and whatsoever Witches can doe) to labour to entertaine and uphold the preaching of the <LOCATION>Gospell</LOCATION>. For where it commeth, downe goeth the power of <LOCATION>Witcherie</LOCATION>, Acts 8. and 13.

Historie likewise tells us, where the <LOCATION>Gospel</LOCATION> came among the hea|then, there the hellish power of <ORGANIZATION>Devils</ORGANIZATION> and spirits greatly dimini|shed, and we heare now by travellers, that in other Countries where the <PERSON>Gospel</PERSON> is not preached, & where they still remaine, (as I may say) according to the abominations of the <ORGANIZATION>Canaanites</ORGANIZATION>, I meane in such places where the <MISC>Heathens</MISC> still remaine, as in the <LOCATION>Indies</LOCATION>, where they by travellers relations, worship the <PERSON>Sunne</PERSON>, <PERSON>Moone</PERSON> and <PERSON>Starrs</PERSON>, Nay I have heard in some places, the <MISC>Devill</MISC> himselfe, and where popery and prophanenesse is, with contempt of Preaching or vile neglect thereof, there <MISC>Witch-craft</MISC> is most rife. Therefore it behooves men to labour to bring forth fruits worthy the <LOCATION>Gospell</LOCATION> and amendment of life. For <PERSON>God</PERSON> hedgeth the vertuous man about, <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> 1. so as <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> cannot come at him, without very speciall licence from <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and that onely for a tryall. The <ORGANIZATION>Angels of God</ORGANIZATION> doe also pitch their tents about such, <LOCATION>Psal</LOCATION>. 34. yea, and have charge over them to keepe them in their waies, <LOCATION>Psal</LOCATION>. 91. 11, 12. And to have religious duties in our families: and as the <ORGANIZATION>Apostle</ORGANIZATION> saith, to pray continually. 1 <ORGANIZATION>Thes</ORGANIZATION>. 5. And as Saint <PERSON>Iames</PERSON> telleth us, <LOCATION>Iam</LOCATION>. 5. 16. that the prayer of a righteous man availeth much if it be servent. <PERSON>David</PERSON> did not onely 3 serve <PERSON>God</PERSON> openly in the <LOCATION>Tabernacle</LOCATION>, but returned home to blesse his house, 2 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 6. 20. And <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> every day sacrificed to <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and san|ctified his children and family. <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> 1. 5. And <PERSON>God</PERSON> gave to <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> a law to sanctifie their houses. And so going ever well armed against these rulers of darkenesse, devills and evill spirits, furnished with the heavenly furniture and spirituall weapons, of which the A|postle speaketh, <LOCATION>Eph</LOCATION>. 6. 14. 18. and being thus qualified, and armed, to trust in <PERSON>God</PERSON> only, who will keepe thee under the shadow of his wings, <ORGANIZATION>Psal</ORGANIZATION>. 91. No man shall neede to feare Witches or Devills; knowing ever this, that they cannot doe the very least harme unto any of the least creatures of <PERSON>God</PERSON> without leave from him: no, not to enter into the heard of swine of the very <PERSON>Gardarens</PERSON>, for surely there is no inchantment in <LOCATION>Iacob</LOCATION>, nor any Divination against <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>. It is the Lord, let him doe what seemeth him good, 2 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 15. 26. It is the Lord that giveth, it is the Lord that taketh away, blessed bee the name of the <LOCATION>Lord</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> 1. 21. And therefore many yeeld thus farre as that <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> needes no provoker to set him forward, as the <MISC>Scripture</MISC> tells us. For the text saith, that he compasseth the world to, and fro, <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> 1. going up and downe like a roaring lyon seeking whom hee may devoure, 1 Pet. 5. 8. He is ready (if <PERSON>God</PERSON> give waie) to bee a lying spirit in the mouth of <MISC>Ahabs Prophets</MISC> to seduce him, 1 King. 22. and to beguile; and that the people which brought the possessed to our <LOCATION>Saviour</LOCATION>, complained only of the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION>, Mat. 15. 2. <LOCATION>Luk</LOCATION>. 9. 39. They made no mention of Witches, nor (for ought we know) had any sus|pition of them, for we find that <PERSON>God</PERSON> hath often sent the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, as the executioner of his displeasure without any meanes of a Witch, as amongst the <MISC>Egyptians</MISC>, he sent evill <ORGANIZATION>Angells</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Psal</ORGANIZATION>. 78. 49. between <LOCATION>Abimelech</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Sichemites</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Judg</PERSON>. 9. 23. So upon <PERSON>Saul</PERSON>, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 16. 15. And so we reade of a <ORGANIZATION>Legion</ORGANIZATION> sent by <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> into the heard of swin, Mat. 5. 12. Thus we see Devills immediately sent from <PERSON>God</PERSON> with|out any instigation of Witches. And therefore conclude that all is from the <MISC>Devill by Gods</MISC> permission, and that there are no Witches at all. But whosoever thou beest that art of this opinion, & although many have gone about to prove that there are no Witches: yet be|sides the former reason, the contrary tenet is undeniable true, that there are Witches.

First, from the lawes that <PERSON>God</PERSON> himselfe hath made against them. First, in forbidding the practice of VVitch-craft, and that none a|mongst his should be <PERSON>VVitches</PERSON>, <PERSON>VVizzards</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Negromancers</ORGANIZATION> and such like, <PERSON>Deut</PERSON>. 18. 10, 11, 12. Secondly in forbidding any to go to them, 4 <ORGANIZATION>Levit</ORGANIZATION>. 19. 20. <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 8. 19. Thirdly, his commandement to put Witches to death, <PERSON>Exod</PERSON>. 22. 18. Fourthly, Gods judgements against them, <PERSON>Deut</PERSON>. 18. 12. which if there were no VVitches what neede these lawes?

Secondly, from the historie of the <ORGANIZATION>Bible</ORGANIZATION>, which nameth to us cer|taine <PERSON>VVitches</PERSON>, as the Socerers of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Exod</LOCATION>. 7. Iannes and <ORGANIZATION>Iam</ORGANIZATION>|bres, 2 <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>. 3. 8. Those in <LOCATION>Babylon</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Persia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dan</PERSON>. 2. 5. 7. <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 47 12. And amongst the <MISC>Nations</MISC> driven out before the children of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Deut</PERSON>. 18. 12, 13. So wee reade of other <MISC>VVitches</MISC> which were, of <ORGANIZATION>Balaam Numb</ORGANIZATION>. 22. <LOCATION>Ios</LOCATION>. 13. 22. Of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, 2 King. 9. 22. Of <LOCATION>Manasses</LOCATION>, 2 <ORGANIZATION>Chron</ORGANIZATION>. 33. 6. Of <PERSON>Simon Magus</PERSON>, Acts 8. 9. And <LOCATION>Elimas</LOCATION>, Acts 13. 8. Secondly, it maketh mention of the practizes of Witches, <LOCATION>Exod</LOCATION>. 7. 2 <ORGANIZATION>Chron</ORGANIZATION>. 33. 6. <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 47. 9. <LOCATION>Eze</LOCATION>. 21. 21. Thirdly, it speaketh of some going to them, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. 7. and sending to them, <LOCATION>Numb</LOCATION>. 22. 5. <LOCATION>Ios</LOCATION>. 24. 9. Fourthly, it relateth how some <ORGANIZATION>Kings</ORGANIZATION> put them to death, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. 3, 9. and cut them off, 2 King. 23. 24. all this should be false If there were no Witches.

Thirdly, from some Comparisons or <LOCATION>Similies</LOCATION> fetched from witch-craft, by <PERSON>Samuel</PERSON>, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 15. and by <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 29. 4. which were absurd if there were no Witches.

Fourthly, (as before) <ORGANIZATION>St Pauls</ORGANIZATION> mentioning <MISC>Witch-craft</MISC> amongst the workes of the flesh, <LOCATION>Gal</LOCATION>. 5. 20.

Fifthly, Gods threatning damnation upon Socerers, Rev. 21. 8.

<PERSON>Sixtly</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Lawes of Nations</ORGANIZATION> both Heathen and <MISC>Christian</MISC> against them.

<PERSON>Seventhly</PERSON>, the truth of <LOCATION>Histories</LOCATION>, and manie relations of their Ar|raignement and conviction.

<LOCATION>Eightly</LOCATION>, experience amongst our selves, and in other <MISC>Countries</MISC>, together with the confession of some of those Witches condemned and executed since May 1645. in the severall Counties afore mentio|ned, Hereafter, herein expressed, I hope will give all sufficient satis|faction that there are Witches.

Now here some may say, this is sufficient to prove that there are Witches in some Countries, or at least have beene in formes times with us here in this Country; but how will you make it appeare that there have been any since the <LOCATION>Gospel</LOCATION> preached amongst us? For many are of oppinion that there are Witches in other Countries where the <LOCATION>Gospel</LOCATION> is not at all, or very little regarded, but where the <LOCATION>Gospel</LOCATION> is faithfully preached as with us in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, &c. that there are not any, no not since the comming of our <LOCATION>Saviour</LOCATION>.

5 I answer that if any man can make it appear that the <PERSON>Gospell</PERSON> frees us from sinne, more then the <MISC>Law</MISC> did our forefathers, that then it might be so. But the <PERSON>Gospell</PERSON> frees us not, and therefore we are as like to have such miscreants amongst us as our Forefathers. For we are as sinful as in the time of the law. And <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> stil remains amongst us. And we are as impatient, profane, and unconscionable as ever, having distempered passions, violent in affection, given to ill company, and vain curiosities, not having respect of <MISC>Religion</MISC>, by which occasions the <MISC>Devill</MISC> taketh advantage and works to have his will, for he goeth thither where he is either sure or hopeth well for entertainment, Mat. 12. 44. He therefore watcheth the time when he may best offer his service to such as any way he finds the least kind of preparednesse in, as when any fall into a passionate sorrow, accompanied with solitarinesse for some losse, as husband, wife, children or such like, the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> offers himself to comfort such in their sorrowfull melancholy mood. So in time of dearth through extreme poverty it many times causeth many to be despe|rately impatient; or so impatient through poverty when they would needs be rich, even against <PERSON>Gods</PERSON> providence, as that they be in such a distempered passion, as they would have their wants satisfied and their desires fulfilled, be it by what means it possible can be, (as I may say) right or wrong; or when one is en|raged with anger, plotting revenge, or is familiar with such as be Witches; As likewise when any are addicted to the reading and studie of dangerous books, inticing to the practice of hidden myste|ries, of <PERSON>Magick</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Inchantments</ORGANIZATION>. Thus by these and such other like means as may be gathered from the confessions of Witches, they prepare themselves for <MISC>Satans</MISC> temptations, to draw them to Witch|craft, as I could instance in those innumerable examples, as you shall read hereafter more at large when I come to speak of what sorts of people are most addicted to Witchcraft; and therefore do you not conceive that there are still such people remaining amongst us? yea certainly there are, and Witches likewise.

But you will still say it doth not yet plainly appear to be so since the <LOCATION>Gospell</LOCATION>, though all these sinnes still remain, for the <MISC>Devil</MISC> needs no provoker as before, for he can, if <PERSON>God</PERSON> permit, greatly trouble us, and can bereave one of his wits, and make one lunatick, deaf, dumb and blind, bow the body together, so that one shall not be a|ble to lift up himself, he can even enter in and possesse any really 6 and make them invincibly strong, and work other effects. Of all which you may read in <LOCATION>Matth</LOCATION>. 9. 32 and 12. 22. and 15 22. and 17. 15. <PERSON>Mark</PERSON>. 1. 23 and 5. 5, 7. and 7 26. and 9. 17, 18, 19, 20, 22, 25, 26 and in <ORGANIZATION>Luke</ORGANIZATION> 4. 35. and 7. 2. and 8. 29, 39. and 11. 14. and 13. 11, 16. and can enter into children, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 13. 16. young folks, <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> 7. 26. Men, <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> 5. 1, 2, 3. women, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 13. 16. <PERSON>Matt</PERSON>. the 15. 22. Yea through the per|mission of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, such as be the elect of <LOCATION>God</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Iob</ORGANIZATION> 1. and 2. A daughter of <PERSON>Abraham</PERSON>, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 13. 11. & <PERSON>Mary Magdalene</PERSON>, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 7. 2. & can counter|feit the resemblance of an holy man, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. 12. 14. 19. yea and for along time, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 8. 27. from a child till one be grown up, <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> 9. 21. even eighteen yeares, <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 13. 16. and so we reade in <PERSON>Luke</PERSON> 7. 2. of seven Devills in one at once, and more <ORGANIZATION>Luke</ORGANIZATION> 11. 26. Yea a whole le|gion, <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> 5. 9, 16, 14. and sometimes the <LOCATION>Lord</LOCATION> is pleased to send De|vills as executioners of his displeasure, as is before expressed.

To this I answer, and grant it for truth, and not to be denyed, but yet notwithstanding all this, there are Witches likewise, and yet the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> doth all this, and more if <PERSON>God</PERSON> permit, for in Gen. 3. We may learne there that the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION> may enter into a dumb creature, & come out of the same, utter a voice intelligible, & offer conference (if any will hearken) to deceive as our Witches now a dayes confesse, and that he chooseth the subtilest creature to deceive by, and the weak|er vessell to confer with, but by the confessions of Witches now lately detected, he chooseth such creatures as they themselves are most addicted to, as you shall hereafter find by their confessions, by the severall shapes he appears in, but how ever we may read there, it was a powerfull perswasion to overcome, and yet work by Witch|es, <PERSON>Wizzards</PERSON>, <MISC>Necromancers</MISC>, Sorcerers, <PERSON>Southsayers</PERSON>, and all kind of <PERSON>Magick</PERSON> art, As we may reade in <LOCATION>Exod</LOCATION>. 7. 11, 12. and 8. 7. Where we may see that Pharaoh called the <MISC>Wisemen</MISC>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sorcerers</ORGANIZATION>, and the <MISC>Magicians</MISC> of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, who did with their inchantments in like man|ner as <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> and <PERSON>Aaron</PERSON>. But I passe by the proofs out of the <MISC>Old Testament</MISC> for this because I desire to give such satisfaction (as I am able) that it may appear that there be Witches now as in former a|ges. And if what hath been already spoken will not give satisfa|ction herein, you may read in the 2. <LOCATION>Tim</LOCATION>. 3. 8. who they were, that were the oppsors of the truth, but such as <ORGANIZATION>Iannes</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Iambres</PERSON>, who withstood <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>, and then search who they were, and you shall find they were such as Pharaoh called to him, as in the before mentioned places, who with their inchantments did the like as <PERSON>Moses</PERSON> had done.

7 So you may read of <LOCATION>Elymas</LOCATION> the <LOCATION>Sorcerer</LOCATION>, Act. 13. 8. who resisted the <MISC>Apostles</MISC> in the time of the <LOCATION>Gospell</LOCATION>.

So likewise in Act. 8 9. you shall read of <LOCATION>Simon Magus</LOCATION> a sorcerer, to whom in the 10 verse it is said, they all gave heed from the least to the greatest, saying, this man is the great power of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, For in the 11. verse its is said, because that of long time he had bewitch|ed them with sorceries, and in the 13 verse we read he was baptised, but read the 20, 21, 22, and you shall read what <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> said to him, and so read no more of him in all the <MISC>New Testament</MISC>.

Also in the Rev. 21. 8. you may read how Sorcerers shall with o|ther sinners there reckoned up, have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimstone.

And so likewise we read in the <ORGANIZATION>Epistle of Iude</ORGANIZATION> the <ORGANIZATION>Apostle</ORGANIZATION> speak|ing there of false Teachers, which were crept into the Church to seduce them, for whose damnable doctrine and manners, horrible judgement was prepared, in the 11. verse pronounceth woe un|to them, for they have gone in the way of <PERSON>Cain</PERSON>, and ranne greedily after the error of <PERSON>Balaam</PERSON>, by which we may plainly see that there were Witches in the time of the <LOCATION>Gospel</LOCATION>, and after the coming and ascension of our <LOCATION>Saviour</LOCATION>, and do any doubt then, whether there be any now? do any think that we be free from such, where sinne and ignorance besides so much abounds? or do you desire to have proof of Witches since then, you shall have enough of their con|fessions to make this evident, besides the relations of learned men writing concerning Witchcraft. But if you would but rightly ob|serve that place in 2. <LOCATION>Tim</LOCATION>. 3. 1 and so on to the 8. you shall find that in the last dayes shall come perillous times, &c. And in the 8. verse it is said, And as <ORGANIZATION>Iannes</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Iambres</PERSON> withstood <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>, so do those also resist the truth. There you may see plainly that there should be such to the latter end, besides in divers other places speak|ing expressely of Witchcraft; as 1. <LOCATION>Tim</LOCATION>. 4. 1. and <ORGANIZATION>Iude</ORGANIZATION> 18.

Likewise of the <MISC>Pythonesse</MISC> which brought her mistris much gain Acts 16. 16. Also in Rev 21. 8. And so I might nominate divers other places, for those which remain doubtfull either of being bewitched or of Witches themselves, but because their own confessions clear this evidently, besides the forenamed places, I proceed to distinguish between those called bad Witches, and those called white or good Witches, which is easily to be discerned and known.

But yet I say all Witches be bad, and ought to suffer alike, being 8 both in league with the Devill: for so is the good, so untruly called, aswell as the other, either open or implicit. And therefore I conclude, all that be in open league with the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> ought to die. And the <MISC>Scripture</MISC> maketh mention onely of ten sorts, which speakes rather of those called the good, which the world so much runnes after, then the other. As we may read: First in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10. 2 <ORGANIZATION>Kings</ORGANIZATION> 17. 1. of a Diviner foreshewing things to come. Such the people delighted in and consulted with, <LOCATION>Ier</LOCATION>. 27. 9. <ORGANIZATION>Ezek</ORGANIZATION>. 21. 22. Such an one was <PERSON>Balaam</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ios</LOCATION>. 13. 22.

Secondly, We read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10. of an Observer of times, or Soothsayer, one which by gaping on the <LOCATION>Heavens</LOCATION> could also foretell something. To these likewise did the people give eare, Ier. 27. 9. And such an one was <PERSON>Manasses</PERSON>, 2 <ORGANIZATION>Chron</ORGANIZATION>. 33. 6. And what was <ORGANIZATION>Elimas</ORGANIZATION> the Sorcerer spoken of in the Acts?

Thirdly, we read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10. of an Observer of times, or searcher out; One which observed times to know when it was best to begin a businesse: as <ORGANIZATION>Hamans Witches</ORGANIZATION> did by casting of lots before him. Of this <PERSON>Manasses</PERSON> also was guilty, 2 <ORGANIZATION>Chro</ORGANIZATION>. 33. 6. To which might be added that in <PERSON>Hester</PERSON>. 3. 7. and 9. 24.

Fourthly, we read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10. <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 47. 12. of a <MISC>Magician</MISC>, one that could deceive the Eye-sight by making something to ap|peare otherwise then it is. Such Pharaoh called to him to oppose <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>. Herein, <PERSON>Iannes</PERSON> and <PERSON>Iambres</PERSON>, of whom Saint <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> speak|eth of, were guilty, and so likewise was <PERSON>Manasses</PERSON>, 2 <ORGANIZATION>Chron</ORGANIZATION>. 33. 6.

Fifthly, we read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 11. of an <MISC>Inchanter</MISC>, or Con|jurer; one joyned in league with another, as the <ORGANIZATION>Witch</ORGANIZATION> is with the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION>. Such an one used <ORGANIZATION>Charmes</ORGANIZATION> to tame Serpents, <ORGANIZATION>Psal</ORGANIZATION>. 58. 5. Many such were in <LOCATION>Babylon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 47. 9. and <ORGANIZATION>Eccl</ORGANIZATION>. 10. 11.

Sixthly, we read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 11. <LOCATION>Lev</LOCATION>. 20. Of one which hath a spirit in him or her which doth give answer to such as come to in|quire of them. Such an one was the <ORGANIZATION>Witch of Endor</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Sam</LOCATION>. 28. Such an one was the <MISC>Pythonesse</MISC> which brought her Mistris much gaine, Acts 16. In <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 29. 4. called a <ORGANIZATION>Whisperer</ORGANIZATION>. To such the people had reguard, <LOCATION>Lev</LOCATION>. 19. 21. and incouraged one another thereunto, <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 8. 19.

<PERSON>Seventhly</PERSON>, wee read in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 11. of a <MISC>Wizzard</MISC>, 1 <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. 9. One also which could foretell some things, and so called for his or her foreknowledge; as now we terme them a wise man, or a wise woman. After this sort the people sought also, <LOCATION>Lev</LOCATION>. 19. 31 and 20. 6.

9 <ORGANIZATION>Eighthly</ORGANIZATION>, we read in <LOCATION>Deu</LOCATION>. 18. 41. of a <MISC>Negromancer</MISC>, one that consulteth with the dead. <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 8. 9.

<LOCATION>Ninthly</LOCATION>, we read in <LOCATION>Isa</LOCATION>. 1 9. 3. of a <LOCATION>VVhisperer</LOCATION>, with secret or soft words, as our white VVitches doe, indeavouring to help man or beast. To these the <MISC>Aegyptians</MISC> sought after, as they did to their Idolls, as in the last forementioned place is expressed. These are now (as I have read) translated Charmers.

<PERSON>Tenthly</PERSON>, we read in <LOCATION>Exod</LOCATION>. 8. 11. of such as Pharaoh sought to, as we call them <PERSON>Iuglers</PERSON>, deceivers, beguiling the eye-sight. Some hold them to be casters of <MISC>Nativities</MISC>, which tell people their for|tune by the time of their birth. These are onely expressed in the <MISC>Old Testament</MISC>: But the <MISC>New</MISC> speaketh, as I may say, onely in generall against <MISC>VVitch-craft</MISC>, which comprehends all the ten a|forementioned. And therefore it cannot be denyed, besides their confessions herafter herein expressed, but that there are such to this time, and that they all ought to suffer alike, which have made an expresse league with the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION>. An art so execrable, to renounce <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and to betake themselves to the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION>, as for this thing onely they deserve death in the highest degree: for the Law of <PERSON>God</PERSON> saith without exception, Thou shalt not suffer a VVitch to live, <PERSON>Exod</PERSON>. 22. 18. If a Witch justly convicted, Death is due to such an one, <PERSON>Levit</PERSON>. 20. 27. For, for those abominations the Lord ut|terly destroyed the <ORGANIZATION>Canaanites</ORGANIZATION>, and plagued <PERSON>Manasses</PERSON>, which wick|nesse of his was so abhorred of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, as in his displeasure hee mentioned it many yeares after, as a cause of removing the <LOCATION>Iewes</LOCATION> from their Land, and of leading them away captive into a strange Land, <LOCATION>Ier</LOCATION>. 15. 4. And did not good King <PERSON>Iosiah</PERSON> put such sorts to death, that he might fulfill the Law? 2 <ORGANIZATION>Kings</ORGANIZATION> 23. 24. And so did <PERSON>Saul</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28. Nay, hath not the Lord threatned great Judgements in the aforementioned places? Yea, and doth he not by the Prophet promise to cut off VVitch-crafts and Soothsay|ers, when he intends to blesse a Nation? Mich. 5. 12.

Now, who they be that make this expresse or open league, are both sorts. But for the hurting and cursing <PERSON>VVitch</PERSON>, there is but one sort. All which makes this expresse or open league; and they doe it onely for mischief, though severall wayes: for they take their Familiars; Some for one mischief, some for another. VVhen as there be two sorts of the other; the one in expresse and open league, for so I tearme it, though made never so secret, because it 10 is done by conference with the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>; And the other is by im|plicit, or secret league, onely by confidence in believing, that such or such a thing shall produce such, or such an effect. Now the first of these two have Familiars, as well as the other, or at least a brand, by which they may be known and discerned by, as well as the first. Some to set spells; Some Charmes; Some to cure dis|eases severall wayes, either by words, or washing clothes, or a|anoynting the <MISC>Instrument</MISC> which gave the wound to cure the wound; Some onely by laying on oft their hands; Some by u|sing and saying superstitious words, or forme of prayers, using good words to bad ends; Some by both; Some by herbes; Some to know where stolen goods be, either by raising the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, or Familiar Spirits; Some onely by words, and so likewise the same for lost goods, or man or beast, and to bring them againe; and so by many such like wayes and meanes doe these worke by: Yet many times they erre, all of these: For the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> cannot per|forme his promises at all times. So that it is not to be questioned, but all these sorts are in league with the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION>. For it is not to be doubted, but before any of them can have power to doe any thing, against, or for any parry, or have any desired ends effe|cted, the league expresse or implicit is first made; bee it expresse then confirmed; but for the Confirmation hereof their confessi|ons will make it plainely appeare, and plaine proofes and reasons for the other, that they confidently trust that their desires shall be effected accordingly to their beliefe, as the curing Witches doe of them which come to them for help. All which I will make plainely appeare, when I come to speake how they may be known. For here some may first demand of mee what sorts of people they be of either sorts?

I answer, as for the first sort most women, and for the other most men. And albeit there be of both sorts of both: as <ORGANIZATION>Elimas</ORGANIZATION> the Sorcerer, and <PERSON>Simon Magus</PERSON>, and so likewise <PERSON>Balaam</PERSON>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Witch of Endor</ORGANIZATION>, and of these young, middle, and old age, of which instances may be given; Yet of Witches in generall, there be commonly more women then men. This is evident.

First, from <MISC>Gods Law</MISC> against Witches, <PERSON>Exod</PERSON>. 22. In the femi|nine gender, praestigiatricem ne sinito vivere.

Secondly, from <PERSON>Sauls</PERSON> speech, when he said, Seeke one out, a woman that hath a familiar spirit, <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>. 28 7. 1 <ORGANIZATION>Chron</ORGANIZATION>. 10 13, 14. in naming a woman and not a man.

11 Thirdly, from experience it is found true here, and in all <LOCATION>Countries</LOCATION>, especially of hurting Witches, that they are most in number, as appeares by their owne confessions, with the stories and relations even from these in our owne <LOCATION>Kingdome</LOCATION>. As of those of <LOCATION>Burton-Old</LOCATION>, where there met above fourescore at a time; And at <LOCATION>Tilbrooke</LOCATION> bushes in <LOCATION>Bedfordshier</LOCATION>, neere adjacent to <LOCATION>Catworth</LOCATION>; in <LOCATION>Huntingtonsheir</LOCATION>, where there met above twenty at one time, as <PERSON>Iohn Wynick</PERSON>, and others confessed who suffered at <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION> last May was two yeares: As also by the confessions of some others which suffered at <LOCATION>Northampton</LOCATION> not long before; So likewise were those which met at <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>, as <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Anne Leech</PERSON> confessed, and those which were condemned, there being about twenty eight, at <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION>, in the summer 1645. were (as I remember) all women. And those at <LOCATION>Bu</LOCATION>|rie Saint <PERSON>Edmunds</PERSON>, where sixtie eight were (as I likewise remem|ber) condemned, most women, All at one <PERSON>Goale</PERSON> delivery, in the summer 1645. So I could nominate farre more instances in other places, and of about two hundred executed since the said May, 1645. in the severall Counties aforementioned, the women farre exceeded the men in number. And as I have read, those in <LOCATION>Lancasheire</LOCATION>, where ninteene assembled, and but two men, and that those that bewitched the <PERSON>Earle</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Rutland</LOCATION> were women; and that those of <LOCATION>Warboyes</LOCATION> were women, and but one man. Women there|fore without question exceed men, especially of the hurting Witches; but for the other, I have knowne more men and have heard such as have gone to them say, almost generally they be men, and so likewise finde them to be so in Authors, which speake of such, and never knew any women questioned in that way but men, and of them as hitherto not many; For as before, men ra|ther uphold them, and say, why should any man be questioned for doing good; but I am certaine the word of <PERSON>God</PERSON> is con|trary.

Now, why it should be that women exceed men in this kind, I will not say, that <MISC>Satans</MISC> setting upon these rather then man is, or like to be, because of his unhappy onset and prevailing with Eve; or their more credulous nature, and apt to bee misled, for that they be commonly impatient, and being displeased more malici|ous, and so more apt to revenge according to their power, and thereby more fit instruments for the <MISC>Devill</MISC>; or that, because they 12 be more ready to be teachers of Witchcraft to others, and to leave it to Children, servants, or to some others (but that you shall finde to be a great inducement thereto by their Confessions) or that, because, where they can command they are more fierce in their rule, and revengefull in setting such on worke whom they can command, wherefore the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> laboureth most to make them Witches: for <MISC>Satan</MISC> is subtill, and seeketh whom he may devoure, and if false teachers.

But as Saint <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> saith, <PERSON>VVitchcraft</PERSON> being amongst the fruits of the flesh, one may fall into this sinne as well as into any other (if <PERSON>God</PERSON> prevent it not) and therefore whether men or women, These sorts following are the aptest, as by experience plainely ap|peares amongst us now a dayes.

I passe by <PERSON>Infidels</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Heathen</PERSON> people in former times (from whom these abominations mentioned in <LOCATION>Deut</LOCATION>. 18. 10, 11. came into <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, and savage <ORGANIZATION>Nations</ORGANIZATION> now (amongst whom) by <LOCATION>Tra</LOCATION>|vellers relations, <PERSON>VVitchcraft</PERSON> is most rise) and will speake onely of such sorts as be called <MISC>Christians</MISC>, and these be,

First, ignorant people whose eyes are blinded by <PERSON>Satan</PERSON>, 2 Cor. 4. 4. and are led captive by him, as is said in another place.

This appeareth in those <LOCATION>VVitches</LOCATION> commonly detected amongst us, silly ignorant persons many of them. <PERSON>Elizabeth Deekes</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Ratlesden</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, a silly ignorant young woman being found with the markes, confessed that she was guilty, and had two crop eared <PERSON>Impes</PERSON>, as she said, which had sucked two or three times upon those markes found upon her, which <PERSON>Impes</PERSON> (she said) came like Mice; the one white, which she called Birds, being the least, the other gray, which she called <ORGANIZATION>Teates</ORGANIZATION>, which <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> asked her to denye <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and told her if she would she should never want, but she said she then refused Whereupon (she said) her mother asked her to give her soule from <PERSON>God</PERSON> to the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION>, which (she said) she likewise refused: but as she was going to bed, either upon a paire of staires, or ladder, her mother pulled her back in much danger of her life, and confessed many other things then more at large. But for her ignorance she was saved at first, when her mother suffered, yet afterward, notwithstanding this, and her refusing those temptations, she confessed, she did make a <MISC>League</MISC> and Covenant with the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and sealed it with her bloud, and imployed those <PERSON>Impes</PERSON>, to the much prejudice of her 13 <ORGANIZATION>Neighbours</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Townsmen</LOCATION>, as she confessed before the <ORGANIZATION>Justice of Peace</ORGANIZATION>. Also <PERSON>Ioane Wallis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Keyston</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Huntingtonsheir</LOCATION>, a ve|ry ignorant, sottish woman, confessed the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> came to her in the likenesse of a man, in blackish cloathing, but had cloven feet, which she called <PERSON>Blackman</PERSON>, who used to lie with her, and have the use of her body, yet she confessed he was more uglier then man, and not as her husband, which speaks to her like a man, but he as he had been some distance from her when he was with her, who told her, if she would be ruled by him she should never want, but should have what she desired, and brought her two others the third time he came, which (she said) she called <PERSON>Grizzell</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Gree</PERSON>|digut, for so (she said) they called themselves, and that those, af|ter shee had consented to the other his demands, and confirmed the Covenant, she could and did imploy as shee then further confessed, both to the <MISC>Townsemen</MISC>, and after to the <MISC>Justice of Peace</MISC>, and some of the mischiefes she had done. Ennumerable of these instances I could nominate in many of their Confessions, as you shall finde in some of those following. But I desire to Answer one objection before I proceed further (that is) some say, and many will and doe say; But you watched them, and kept them from meat, drinke, or rest, and so made them say what you would. A very unnaturall part so to use <MISC>Christians</MISC>. I answer so it were. But I never knew any deprived of meat, drinke or rest, but had what was sitting till they were carried before some <ORGANIZATION>Justice of Peace</ORGANIZATION> to be examined, and had provision to rest upon, as bolsters, pillowes, or <MISC>Cushions</MISC>, and such like, if they were kept where no beds were; yet I doe not deny but at first, some were kept two, three, or foure dayes, perchance somewhat baser, but then it hath been, either when no <ORGANIZATION>Justice of Peace</ORGANIZATION> was neere, or when the witnesses against them could not goe sooner, but then they have had beds, and for other provision, I never knew any kept, of what ranke or qua|lity soever, but that they had better provision, either meate or drinke, then at their own houses. For the watching, it is not to use violence, or extremity to force them to confesse, but onely the keeping is, first, to see whether any of their spirits, or familiars come to or neere them; for I have found, that if the time be come, the spirit or <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> so called should come, it will be either visible or invisible, if visible, then it may bee discerned by those in the <PERSON>Roome</PERSON>, if invisible, then by the party. Secondly, it is for this 14 end also, that if the parties which watch them, be so carefull that none come visible, nor invisible but may be discerned, if they follow their directions, then the party presently after the time their Familiars should have come, if they faile, will presently con|fesse, for then they thinke they will either come no more, or at least have forsaken them.

Thirdly, it is also to the end, that <PERSON>Godly Divines</PERSON> and o|thers might discourse with them, and idle persons be kept from them, for if any of their society come to them to discourse with them, they will never confesse; This was observed at <LOCATION>Bury Saint Edmunds</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, as I remember, when there were eighteene to be executed; most of them kept in a <LOCATION>Barne</LOCATION> together, they made a Covenant amongst themselves, not to confesse a word next day at the gallowes, when they were to be hanged, notwithstanding they had formerly confessed, and some of them after they came into the <LOCATION>Goale</LOCATION>, and some before the <LOCATION>Bench</LOCATION> and Country, but most of them (if not all) before the <MISC>Justices of the Peace</MISC>, and so dyed next day accordingly very desperately, except one pe|nitent woman which refused their Covenant or agreement: so she made it knowne, and how they made a singing of a <MISC>Psalme</MISC> after they had done it. But if honest godly people discourse with them, laying the hainousnesse of their sins to them, and in what condition they are in without <MISC>Repentance</MISC>, and telling them the subtilties of the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and the mercies of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, these wayes will bring them to Confession without extremity, it will make them breake into Confession hoping for mercy.

Now that the <MISC>Impes</MISC> come visible, it is true and apparent, and so watching hath produced true and strange effects, and is a great meanes (under <PERSON>God</PERSON>) to bring them to confession, as for exam|ple; <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>, being kept three dayes and three nights, shee confessed many things, but how she was kept I know not well, for I came not at her during that time, notwithstanding I lived then in <LOCATION>Towne</LOCATION>, and was one which caused her to be questioned, who did accuse some others which lived in their severall <LOCATION>Parishes</LOCATION>, the <MISC>Townsemen</MISC> desired me to goe with her confession taken in writing by another, to the <MISC>Justices of the Peace</MISC> for a warrant for those she accused, the warrant was made for the searching of such persons as I should nominate, whereupon, I would first goe to her before the Warrant should 15 be served, to know of her who she did accuse; Mr. <PERSON>Hopkin</PERSON> be|ing with mee went together, and when I had asked her who shee had accused, we were agoing away; but she said to us, if you will stay, I will shew you my <LOCATION>Impes</LOCATION>, for they bee ready to come. Then said Mr. <PERSON>Hopkin</PERSON> <PERSON>Besse</PERSON>, will they doe us no harme? no said she, what? did you thinke I am afraid of my children? you shall sit downe, so wee did, where she appointed us. Then one of the company which was appointed to be with her that night, said to her, <PERSON>Besse</PERSON>, I asked you a question of late, but you answered not, then she said, what is it? Then he replyed and said, tell the truth, if it be the truth, say so. but if not truth, then say so, Hath not the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> had the use of your body? she said, why should you aske such a question? he answerd, I desire to know the truth and no otherwise, then she fetched a sigh, and said, it is true, then said Mr. <PERSON>Hopkin</PERSON>, in what manner and likenesse came he to you? shee said, like a tall, proper, black haired gentleman, a properer man then your selfe, and being asked which she had rather lie withall, shee said the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and so particularized every thing, and how hee came in, and his habit, and how he lay with her, and spoke to her, as she then affirmed to bee truth, and so presently fell a smacking with her lips and called <PERSON>Lought</PERSON> two or three times, which presently appeared to us eight (For there were six which were appointed to bee with her that night before we went) in the likenesse of a Cat, as she had formerly told us; for she told us before what shapes they should come in, and so that presently vanished; then she called againe as before, <PERSON>Jermarah</PERSON>, then appeared another, like a red or sandie spotted dog, with legs not so long as a finger (to our perceivance) but his back as broad as two dogs, or broader, of that bignesse, and vanished, and so after that called more, as before, by their severall names, which came in severall shapes, One like a <ORGANIZATION>Greyhound</ORGANIZATION>, with legs as long as a <ORGANIZATION>Stagge</ORGANIZATION>; Another like a Ferrit; And one like a <ORGANIZATION>Rabbit</ORGANIZATION>, and so in severall shapes they appeared to us, till there were some se|ven or eight seen; Some by some of us, and others by other some of us; then I asked her if they were not all come, for there were more come then she spoke of, she answered that they came dou|ble in severall shapes, but said, one was still to come, which was to teare mee in peeces, then I asked her why, she said, because I would have swome her, and told me that now shee would bee 16 even with mee, and so told in what manner it should come, black, and like a <MISC>Toade</MISC>, and so afterward did come, as the rest averred that saw it, and so she confessed their meetings, and the manner how they worshipped the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> at their meetings, and said to us, they that be found with these markes that I am found with|all, are without question Witches, yet said, that there might be some Witches which had not those markes; but affirmed it over and over again, that all those that had those markes were Witches, and had familiar spirits which sucked of them, and so confessed what mischiefe she had done with her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, in a very large man|ner, and so did next day, after she had slept; for the <ORGANIZATION>Justice</ORGANIZATION> gave me order that she should sleepe before he examined her, lest shee had not slept before, and so I did accordingly, and yet shee then confessed at large before two <MISC>Justices of the Peace</MISC>, and how shee would have been my death; this was the first accused, and her markes and confession, the beginning of our knowledge: Yet I confesse, the markes be difficult to finde from naturall markes, as I shall hereafter declare. <LOCATION>Rebecca West of Lamford</LOCATION>, in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>, who was (as she confessed) married to the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and the manner, had an <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> came to her in the time she was kept, but of her confession more at large hereafter. Also <PERSON>Elizabeth Finch</PERSON> of Wat|son in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, confessed, that about twenty yeares before shee was found with the markes, the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> appeared to her in the likenesse of a smoaky coloured Dog, which asked her to deny <PERSON>God</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, which she said, upon his promises she did, and let him have bloud to seale, or confirme the Covenant or agree|ment; and that soone after that, there came two more, black on the backs and reddish on the bellies, which sucked her two or three times a week, upon those markes that were found on her, and that sometimes she fetched bloud in other places for them, and gave it to them; shee also had her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION> came visible; For she confessed in the time shee was kept, one which was with her to looke to her, saw one of them, and flung it into the fire, which she affirmed was one of her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, and that whilest they were busie about that, thinking to burne it, she confessed the o|ther came, and threw her out of the chaire she sate in, which hurt her forehead and wrest, which was done accordingly, and so further confessed. Of these I could bring diverse instances, but I will proceed. They come likewise invisible; as one <PERSON>Binkes</PERSON> of Ha|verill 17 had an <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> sucking of her whilst she was talking with o|thers, and presently confessed it Another whilest I was in the roome with her, at <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION>, I perceived by her carriage that she was asucking her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, Spirits, or Familiars so called; I lay|ed it to her charge, but she denied it: Yet presently after she con|fessed it was truth, when she was asked by the <ORGANIZATION>Justice of Peace</ORGANIZATION>. And as I remember, it was the same woman; but I am sure of <LOCATION>Keyston</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Huntingtonshier</LOCATION>, and so was she, that to the thinking of two which were with her, she sate still in her chaire, when two more in the yard saw her goe out into the yard, and her going in againe; This woman confessed the <MISC>Devill</MISC> sate in her likenesse, and she went out, and suckled her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION> in the yard, as the other two affirmed. So in the same <PERSON>Towne</PERSON>, one <ORGANIZATION>Clarkes</ORGANIZATION> wife skipped out at a hole in a stone wall, above halfe a foot thick, which was some nine Inches long, and some foure and a halfe broad, all the one side head and all, and but little to bee seen of her but one leg; and the hole was neere a yard and halfe from the ground, and yet one pulled her back againe, and afterward went away, no body knew how: yet I say, if those which looke to them be carefull, it is to be discerned; this is apparent by that I nomina|ted at <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION>. And so at <LOCATION>Codman</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, being told how a woman there carried her selfe, I caused her to be searched a|gaine, and there was alteration of the markes, and the woman presently confessed it, and made a large confession; and so it hath been common in all our proceedings, and a great cause for keep|ing them; for the bloud hath sometimes been found on the end of the marke, or to be stroked ou't when they be taken on a sud|daine, As I could instance the one halfe of their confessions; but because it is so apparent, I instance no further. But now to ma|nifest that good <PERSON>Counsell</PERSON> will doe it, and so likewise without keeping; for I hold they two depend most upon one: Then say I, that upon good exhortations after the markes found, they may be brought to confession, either by keeping, though every thing necessary be afforded them, as I never did otherwise, but now lately keepe none, or not above one night till we goe thence, and yet have their confessions. Witnesse those executed at <LOCATION>Elie</LOCATION>, a litle before <PERSON>Michaelmas</PERSON> last, who made large confessions. Also one at <LOCATION>Chatterish</LOCATION> there; One at March there; And another at <LOCATION>Wim</LOCATION>|blington there, now lately found, still to be tryed, who made very 18 large confessions, especially the first two; <PERSON>Nicholas Hempstead</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Greeting</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, being found, upon exhortations, and laying the hainousnesse of the sinne, and <ORGANIZATION>Gods Judgements</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Gods</PERSON> mercie, and the like, notwithstanding hee at first railed on me in very approbious tearmes, yet presently sent for me, and would have asked mee forgivenesse, he presently confessed that hee had made a league and Covenant with the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and how hee had confirmed it with his bloud; And the shape of his <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, and of the <MISC>Devill</MISC> when they covenanted, and how he killed a horse of one of the <LOCATION>Constables</LOCATION>, because he pressed him for a souldier, and five of the best horses in <MISC>Colonell Rochesters Troope</MISC>; And di|vers other things he had done, making a very large confession, with a great deale of penitency and sorrow, which hee so conti|nued in (as I since heard) to his very execution without alte|ration. To this I might adde, <PERSON>Henry Carrs</PERSON> hereafter mentioned; And the boyes next, after the objections answered, and diverse o|thers which you shall here finde; but because it falleth out better, when I shall speake how to discover them, I leave here, hoping this is sufficient for that objection, if not, I will answer more ful|ly, as occasion shall serve. But then some will say, you swome some of them, especially at the first, was not that extremity? I an|swer, that hath been used, and I durst not goe about to cleere my selfe of it, because formerly I used it, but it was at such time of the yeare as when none tooke any harme by it, neither did I ever doe it but upon their owne request; and were to such as first were found with the markes; but now lately, there hath been no such course taken that I know of. For I am of opinion, that it is one way of distrusting of <LOCATION>Gods</LOCATION> providence, putting confidence that that shall bring such or such an effect, or event; neither was it e|ver given in or taken, that I know, as an evidence against any, nor used by any of us but the first summer, from March, or May 1645. to about the middle of August next following; when Judge Cor|bolt that now is, forwarned it; When Divines gave their opinion of the unlawfulnesse thereof, it hath ever since been left, and not many before so used: Notwithstanding, it was then the desire of such persons themselves, thinking thereby to cleare themselves, whereas it fell out otherwise. Yet under favour, Let me speake one thing that I have found in that way; that it is a true rule in one respect, that the vvater entreth not into any of them, when 19 it will into a free person, though they swimme both alike; for so they will, if the water be inchanted, but the free person will presently be choaked, when the other lye topling on the water, striving to get their heads, or themselves under the water, but cannot, neither can they bring out water in their mouthes, though they be foretold of it, nor spit cleare water; for the water enters them not when it will the other Thus farre I have observed, or further: But because it is held unlawfull, I should be sorry to speake any thing, either to give offence to any, or to be a meanes to animate any in such courses. For if any did confesse, rather then to goe into the water, or to come out of the water, or pre|sently after, except they had been shifted, and refreshed every way, and knowne to be in perfect memory, it hath been taken as no evidence; and so hath all other forcement been. But there is one, a very remarkable thing concerning this, that was done at <LOCATION>Saint Neotts</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Huntingtonshire</LOCATION>, of a woman that had been searched two or three times, and not found, for they can hide their markes sometimes, as you shall heare after herein, yet was still in great sus|picion of many of the <MISC>Townsmen</MISC> to be guilty (the brand is diffi|cult to finde if she had notice) and the rather, for that she fled, or went away after she was searched twice, for some are not found at first, yet be in the end: So at her returne some vvould swim her, and did, she swum apparently, where they had formerly cast a free|man in, tyed after the same manner, she was not further medled with then. But as I have heard, and in part from the man himself, where the act should be done, A Dog was seen in his yard, which a <MISC>Mastie Dog</MISC> would not seize on, but his son stroke at the Dog, and hatt him two or three blowes over the back, up to the shoulders|ward, presently a gelt bitch seized on him, and bit him on the neck, and gave him some shuckes, and then the Dog got away: so it remained, but this woman not being seen in the street as formerly, was caused to be viewed; and found bitten on the neck, or bruised on the other parts in a most fearfull manner. These are some similitudes, that there is something in swimming (if lawfull) but to proceed. This one more, that ignorant peo|ple are most apt to be Witches, as afore said. Of a Boy in <LOCATION>Ratles</LOCATION>|don aforesaid, who was accused, when he was under nine yeares of age, when all know he could not be of much capacity, hee without watching, or keeping, voluntarily confessed, that hee 20 suckled an <PERSON>Impe</PERSON>, and had it at command to doe mischiefe, and no|minated some, as the killing of some <LOCATION>Chickings</LOCATION>, and some o|ther mischiefes he had then done, as he confessed, together with the reasons he caused his <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> to kill the <MISC>Chickens</MISC>, which was, because the man which owed them had chidden him for spoyling his grasse, when, as he said, they did it, so the next time he saw them there, he did it. This boy being young, I (suppose the Jury had hopes of his amendment, as I confesse I then had) he was then released, and vvent to the <LOCATION>Towne</LOCATION> againe, where he continued some time, and was suspected againe for further mis|chiefe, and so apprehended againe, and put into prison, where he then voluntarily confessed likewise his renewing of the league and Covenant with the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and the sealing of it with his bloud, after his mother vvas hanged; for she suffered for Witch|craft, about the Michaelmas 1645. and then was the first questio|ned, and that he had more familiar spirits, or <LOCATION>Impes</LOCATION>, as they call them, and that the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> appeared to him, in the likenesse of a black brovvne <PERSON>Mare</PERSON>, and would carrie him whither hee desired, and confessed abundance of mischiefe he had done, between the time he was released, and committed againe. But after hee was in <PERSON>Burie Goale</PERSON>, not long before the <ORGANIZATION>Assizes</ORGANIZATION>, the first since these warres, the <PERSON>Goaler</PERSON> missing a Prisoner in the morning, which he had over night, a notorious offender, whom he kept double shackled, the <PERSON>Goaler</PERSON> questioned this boy, and upon some threat|ning speeches, the boy confessed, that he was gone home on his <ORGANIZATION>Mare</ORGANIZATION> over the walls, and shewed where, and told him he should finde him with his wife; whereupon, the <PERSON>Goaler</PERSON> sent forthwith to the Prisoners house, being at least twelve miles, and there found him at his house, as the boy had said, having shackles on as he went out. Will this with the other give you satisfaction? but I might adde to this, superstitious and Idolatrous persons. But I passe, intending onely to take the heads, agreeing with the confessions of Witches.

Secondly, malicious people, full of revenge, having hearts swolne with rancour, upon the least displeasure, with bitter ban|nings and curses, threatning revenge or requitalls; this is manifest by the nature, quality, words, and deeds of Witches convicted, who have shewed themselves to be such, as ever found so to be, as the said <PERSON>Iohn Wynnick</PERSON> confest, that when hee lived 21 at <LOCATION>Thrapston</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Northamptonsheir</LOCATION>, he having lost his purse with some seven shillings in it, as he was in a <PERSON>Barne</PERSON>, where he lived, there in an Inne, as hee was making up of bottles of hay, hee was in a passion for his purse and money, and in such a rage of banning and cursing, that he was saying to himselfe, would hee knew where he might goe to a cunning man for it, for have it he would, though he went to the <LOCATION>Devill</LOCATION> for it; (here was a pre|parednesse for the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION>) for he confessed, the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> appeared to him immediately, in the likenesse of a <PERSON>Beare</PERSON>, but not above the bignesse of a <ORGANIZATION>Rabbit</ORGANIZATION>, vvhich told him, if hee would fall downe and worship him, he would help him to his purse, and money a|gaine, and that he should have it where he stood, next day about the same time; so he did fall downe and worship him; And next day he came againe, to see for his purse and money, and found it accordingly, but confessed, that before he could tell it, the De|vill in the same shape appeared to him againe, and told him, hee must fall downe and worship him againe, and then he fell downe, and said, Oh my Lord, my <PERSON>God</PERSON>, I thanke thee, and then hee asked him to deny <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and to serve him as Lord, and then he should never want, vvhich he confessed he con|sented to, then he demanded bloud, and he bade him take it, so he skipped on his shoulder, and fetched bloud with his claw, on the side of his head, which marke was seen at his Tryall; Then he confessed, there appeared two more, vvhich the first told him hee must worship also, and take them for his Gods, and they should be at his command, and so he said, he did; then that like a <PERSON>Beare</PERSON> turned like a <PERSON>Ratt</PERSON>, and so those sucked on the three marks I found on him, after to the time he was taken, at their times ap|pointed, and vvere at his command, as he then confessed more at large, before the <MISC>Justices of the Peace</MISC>, and confessed at the Gal|lowes likewise, the last words he spoke. Also one <PERSON>Moores</PERSON> wife of <PERSON>Sutton</PERSON>, in the <ORGANIZATION>Isle of Elie</ORGANIZATION>, in the <LOCATION>County of Cambridge</LOCATION>, after she had confessed the league and Covenant made, and sealed vvith her bloud, confessed, that she sent one of her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION> to kill a man, or at least to hurt to him; for that she had bought a <PERSON>Pigge</PERSON> of him, for two shillings and two pence, and paid him two shillings, and afterward he comming by her dore, asked her for it, which man, was soone after taken sick, and in his sicknesse, cryed out of her, saying, he could not depart this life, untill hee had spoken with 22 her, so she was sent for, but she refused, whereupon (he lying in such extremity) she was by some of his friends, at his request, being so desirous to speake with her in such extremity, forced to goe to him, and then soone after he dyed, according as hee for|merly said; So this woman confessed divers other things, and seemed to be very penitent, and sorry for it; for she wept at her tryall, and confessed her selfe guilty before the Judge, <PERSON>Bench</PERSON>, and Country; But what she did after, or at her Execution, I know not. <PERSON>Thomazine Ratcliffe</PERSON> of <PERSON>Shellie</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, confessed, that it was malice that had brought her to that she was come to, meaning Witchcraft; for she confessed, that soone after her husbands de|cease, above twenty yeares before her confession, there came one in the likeuesse of a man, into bed to her, which spoke with a hollow, shrill voyce, and told her, he would be a loving husband to her, if she would consent to him, which she said, she did, and then he told her, he would revenge her of all her ene|mies, and that she should never misse any thing, in which she said, she found him a lyer, but said, that <PERSON>Satan</PERSON> often tempted her to banning, swearing, and cursing, which shee confessed she did use a long time, and that many times it fell out accord|ingly, and that she, falling out with one <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>'s wife, who had a child drowned, for that she called her <ORGANIZATION>Witch</ORGANIZATION>, saying, she was the cause of the childs drowning, she bad her goe home and look to the rest, lest she lost more, and one died suddenly after. Also <PERSON>Anne Randall</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lauenham</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, after she had confessed the Covenant, for still you must remember, that is first done, before the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, or their Familiars, or <PERSON>Impes</PERSON>, act, or doe any thing, confessed that she had two <MISC>Impes</MISC>, which were heavie and soft, but came in the likenesse of <LOCATION>Cats</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Kitlins</LOCATION>, of a blew colour, cal|led <ORGANIZATION>Hangman</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Iacob</PERSON>, and that those sucked on the markes were found upon her body, some thirty yeares together: some|times once a weeke, sometimes once a fortnight, and that shee sent her <PERSON>Impe Hangman</PERSON> to kill a horse of one <ORGANIZATION>William Baldwins</ORGANIZATION> of <PERSON>Thorpe</PERSON>, some two miles from <LOCATION>Lauenham</LOCATION>, for that she asked him to bring her in some wood, and he bad her pay for that she had had first; and the <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> returned, and told her he had done, he had killed two, for they were lanquelled together, so he killed them both, which horses were killed (but in such a tempest) as was supposed by a <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Thunder</LOCATION>, untill she confessed it of 23 her selfe. Also she confessed, that being at <LOCATION>Stephen Humfries</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Thorpe</LOCATION> aforesaid, and a begging for <PERSON>Almes</PERSON>, hee came home well, and she being at the doore, he chid her, or gave her such words as she liked not of; As she went over the way from the house, her <PERSON>Impe Hangman</PERSON> appeared to her, and asked her what he should doe, and she bad him goe and kill one of his <ORGANIZATION>Hogs</ORGANIZATION>, which shee saw, which she said he did before she was out of fight, which Hog died accordingly. Likewise she further confessed, that she being angry with one Mr. <PERSON>Coppinger</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lavenham</LOCATION>, she sent her <PERSON>Impe Iacob</PERSON> to carry away bushes, which he had caused to be laid to fence his fences, above one load, here some, and there some, all along by the hedge side, as they were to be hedged out, and in one night they were gone, no man knew what way, untill such time as she confessed her <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> did it. But as I have since heard, they were knowne to be in another mans ground, who confessed, they came the same night, but how, he knew not till then. Also a young man of <LOCATION>Denford</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Northampuonshire</LOCATION>, who suffered for Witchery since the said time, at <LOCATION>Northampton</LOCATION>, Confessed, that he sent one of his <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, to one <PERSON>Cockes Cattell</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Denford</LOCATION>, be|cause he would not let him keep them, and the <PERSON>Cattell</PERSON> ranne so violently away foming, that the owner had much adoe to catch them with a horse, and more to get them home into his yard a|gaine; and so many other things he confessed, as I could parti|cularly instance. And so for this, I hope it is sufficient, to give all satisfaction, for all confessions, or most of them at least, tend to prove this in some part. Those that are given to over much curiosity, to seeke after vaine Knowledge, in pride of heart to goe beyond others, to understand secret and hidden things, to know things to come. Such are those, as not bound|ing themselves within the limits of reason, nor of <LOCATION>Gods</LOCATION> reveal|ed will, fall fowle unawares upon the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON>, and are in great danger to be intrapped by him, and made his slaves by his intice|ments. Thus was <PERSON>Parson Lowis</PERSON> taken, who had been a Minister, (as I have heard) in one <LOCATION>Parish</LOCATION> above forty yeares, in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, before he was condemned, but had been indited for a common imbarriter, and for Witchcraft, above thirty yeares before, and the grand Jury (as I have heard) found the bill for a common im|barriter, who now, after he was found with the markes, in his confession, he confessed, that in pride of heart, to be equall, or 24 rather above <PERSON>God</PERSON>, the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> tooke advantage of him, and hee covenanted with the <ORGANIZATION>Devill</ORGANIZATION>, and sealed it with his bloud, and had three Familiars or spirits, which sucked on the markes found upon his body, and did much harme, both by <ORGANIZATION>Sea and Land</ORGANIZATION>, especially by Sea; for he confessed, that he being at <LOCATION>Lan</LOCATION>|garfort in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, where he preached, as he walked upon the wall, or workes there, he saw a great saile of Ships passe by, and that as they were sailing by, one of his three <MISC>Impes</MISC>, namely his yel|low one, forthwith appeared to him, and asked him what hee should doe, and he bade it goe and sinke such a Ship, and shew|ed his <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> a new Ship, amongst the middle of the rest (as I re|member) one that belonged to <ORGANIZATION>Ipswich</ORGANIZATION>, so he confessed the <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> went forthwith away, and he stood still, and viewed the Ships on the <LOCATION>Sea</LOCATION> as they were a sayling, and perceived that Ship immedi|ately, to be in more trouble and danger then the rest; for he said, the water was more boystrous neere that then the rest, tumbling up and downe with waves, as if water had been boyled in a pot, and soone after (he said) in a short time it sanke directly downe into the <LOCATION>Sea</LOCATION>, as he stood and viewed it, when all the rest sayled away in safety, there he confessed, he made fourteen widdowes in one quarter of an houre. Then Mr. <PERSON>Hopkin</PERSON>, as he told me (for he tooke his Confession) asked him, if it did not grieve him to see so many men cast away, in a short time, and that he should be the cause of so many poore widdowes on a suddaine; but he swore by his maker, no, he was joyfull to see what power his <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION> had, and so likewise confessed many other mischiefes, and had a charme to keep him out of <LOCATION>Goale</LOCATION>, and hanging, as he paraphrased it himselfe, but therein the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> deceived him; for he was hanged, that <PERSON>Michaelmas</PERSON> time 1645. at <LOCATION>Burie</LOCATION> Saint <PERSON>Edmunds</PERSON>, but he made a very farre larger confession, which I have heard hath been printed; but if it were so, it was neither of Mr. <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> doing, nor mine owne; for we never printed any thing untill now. I doe this (he being dead) but make no use of any confessions taken by him, but only this, for that it fal|leth out so fit for this purpose: Yet I have heard, that other con|fessions have been printed, and some other things besides, as if it had been of ours, or one of our doings, or at least, by one of our consents; when as I know, he never had any hand in any, and for my part I utterly renounce all former. Also I may adde 25 to this, one <PERSON>Henry Carre</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Ratlesden</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, who I have heard was a <PERSON>Scholler</PERSON> fit for <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, (if not a <PERSON>Cambridge Scholler</PERSON>) and was well educated; yet fell into this grievous sinne, and confessed, that he had two <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION>, which sucked on those markes I found upon him, two yeeres together, and came in the likenesse of <ORGANIZATION>Mice</ORGANIZATION>, which he felt oft, and said, they were hairy and heavie, and so seeming to bewaile his condition, said, that he had forsaken <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>God</PERSON> him, and therefore would confesse no more, he said, untill he came on the <MISC>Gallowes</MISC> to be hanged, for he had confessed enough for that, and then he would confesse all, and make all other knowne he knew of, but in the meane time, he would confesse no more, nor did; yet he was much importuned to it, but that was alwayes his an|swer, and was arraigned at the <PERSON>Barre</PERSON>, three or foure times, and yet by reason of an <ORGANIZATION>Allarum</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, the <MISC>Goale</MISC> delivery at <LOCATION>Burie Saint Edmunds</LOCATION> was adjourned, for about three weekes, and he 톎ied in the <LOCATION>Goale</LOCATION> in that time: So it was conceived to be pride of heart, which was the first originall cause, by reason of his knowledge; yet I confesse, he fell into poverty before his death, but as for that, I thinke it is seldome or never knowne, that any get estates, or thrive, that thus give themselves over to <PERSON>Satan</PERSON>, but rather consume their estates, if they have any: yet the word of <PERSON>God</PERSON> sayes, The wicked man thriveth as well as the godly in this world: But for Witches, I never knew any. To these likewise might be added, those observers of times, <PERSON>Deut</PERSON>. 18. And such as professe to cure diseases, by such meanes as have no reason, or worke of nature to doe the Cure, nor have by any ordinance of <PERSON>God</PERSON>, from his word, any such operation to heale the infirmity. And therefore such remedies must be <PERSON>Diabolicall</PERSON>, & the practisers either Witches already, or by their implicit faith, the next doore to <LOCATION>Witchchraft</LOCATION>. Such be they that use Spells, <PERSON>Charmes</PERSON>, and such like; and what be <PERSON>Juglers</PERSON> and legerdemain Companions? For that they sport with such resemblances, and utter words, as the invocating of a Spirit, the reality whereof, is called an abomination before <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and as Saint <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> speaketh, Children of disobedience. What be the Fortune tellers, and such like? but apt to be <MISC>Satans</MISC> slaves in <LOCATION>Witchery</LOCATION>, as they be his o|therwise in impiety; For through curiosity of knowledge, if reason and, <ORGANIZATION>Art</ORGANIZATION> faile, will it not move men to seeke help of a Spi|rit, 26 who is ready at hand to attend, to draw them into the pit of <PERSON>Magick</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Sorcery</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Witchchraft</PERSON>? as one Mr. <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> speaketh of, in his booke, called, <ORGANIZATION>The Mystery of Witchcraft</ORGANIZATION>, Whom himselfe was delivered from, by <MISC>Gods</MISC> preventing grace; but be|cause as yet, these have not been so commonly found out now a|dayes, I forbeare further, though I might instance diverse exam|ples more. Those who with greedinesse gape after worldly wealth, or feare poverty. As <ORGANIZATION>Meribell Bedford</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Ratlesden</LOCATION> aforesaid con|fessed, that above six yeares before she was found with the markes, which Witches usually have, There came a black thing to her, and called <PERSON>Meribell</PERSON>, which asked her to denie <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and told her, if she would, she should never want, but should bee avenged of all her enemies, which she consented to: then she said, he had bloud of one of her little fingers, to seale the <ORGANIZATION>Covenant</ORGANIZATION>, which being done, she said, foure more came, One like a <MISC>Dow</MISC>, called <ORGANIZATION>Tib</ORGANIZATION>; One like a <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> called Tom; One like a <ORGANIZATION>Spider</ORGANIZATION>, or a <MISC>Spinner</MISC> called Ioane; and the other like a <LOCATION>Waspe</LOCATION> called <PERSON>Nann</PERSON>; These she confessed were at her command, to performe the Covenant, and did suck upon those markes found upon her body, two or three times a week, during the said six yeares, and did much harme, as she freely confessed with much penitency. To this I may adde, one <PERSON>Elizabeth Hubbard</PERSON>, widdow, of <ORGANIZATION>Stow Market in Suffolke</ORGANIZATION>, who confessed, that above thirty yeares, she had three things came to her in the likenesse of Children, which asked her whispering to deny <PERSON>God</PERSON>, <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and all his workes, and to cleave to them, and she should want nothing; These she said, as they named themselves, were called, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Hobb</PERSON>, and that they scratched her back, and fetched bloud to seale the Covenant, and that they use to suck on those markes which were found upon her, two or three times a week, about breake of the day, and that she did say, I pray to <PERSON>God</PERSON> to doe to him as he dealt by me (meaning a man of the same <ORGANIZATION>Towne</ORGANIZATION>) and he languished and died, and many other things she said she did, but was ashamed to tell them. Alice the wife of <PERSON>Edmund Wright</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Hitcham</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, confessed that she had foure <MISC>Impes</MISC> above threescore yeares; two like little <PERSON>Boyes</PERSON>; one like a <PERSON>Lambe</PERSON>, and the fourth like a gray <PERSON>Buzzard</PERSON>, and that the biggest boy spoke to her with a great whorce voyce, as if he had been griev'd, and asked her to goe into the field, and 27 she should have money, and should never misse or want any thing, and asked her to deny <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and to curse <PERSON>God</PERSON> two or three times, and that she tooke her elder brother with her, and went into the field, but when they came to the place where they appointed her to goe, they found none, and that she uses often to be in paine and trouble, after they had nipped or sucked her, where her markes were found, sometimes once a week, some|times once a fortnight, and that she felt on them, and that they were soft, and that they came sometimes severally, sometimes al|together, and that they often asked her to goe and doe mischief, which she confessed, to some <PERSON>Cattell</PERSON> of her <PERSON>Neighbours</PERSON>, and said, that she was much troubled and tormented, and in extreame paine, which they have put her to for denying their demands. Furthermore, <PERSON>Ioane Ruce</PERSON> ulver of <LOCATION>Powstead</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, confessed, that in the field called <PERSON>Horsecrost</PERSON> or <LOCATION>Hog-Marsh</LOCATION>, there appeared in a bush things like <PERSON>Chickens</PERSON>, about five or six, and that she catched three of them and the rest ranne away, and that she car|ried three home, which soone after turned to the likenesse of <ORGANIZATION>Mice</ORGANIZATION>, whose names she called Touch, <PERSON>Pluck</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Take</PERSON>, which spoke to her with a great hollow voyce, and asked her to denie <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, and told her, if she would, she should never want meat, drinke, or clothes, or money, but she said she told them, that if she denied <PERSON>God</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>, she should lose her soule, but she said, they told her againe, they were more able to save her soule then <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and that they would doe more for her then she thought for, if she would consent to them, which then she confessed she did, and then they demanded bloud, and she nip|ped her fore-finger, and they pricked her finger with a pin, and there dropped six drops of bloud which they catched, and so had it againe after the same manner thrice, and that she did agree to give them her soule; Then I asked her whether they brought her any money or no, and she said, sometimes foure shil|lings at a time, and sometimes six shillings at a time, but that is but seldome, for I never knew any that had any money before, except of <ORGANIZATION>Clarkes</ORGANIZATION> wife of <PERSON>Manningtree</PERSON>, who confessed the same, and shewed some which she said her <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> brought her, which was perfect money: But this <PERSON>Ruce</PERSON>, further confessed the sucking of her markes, and how she sent her <ORGANIZATION>Impe Touch</ORGANIZATION> to kill a <PERSON>Bullock</PERSON>, and that he came back againe, and told her he had stuck it on the 28 right side, and it died accordingly, and so many other things, and said she was stopped and could not confesse when she would, but after had ease. Here you may observe, that if he cannot pre|vaile for want, then he promises to free them of hell torments, and so delude them that way. As he did <PERSON>Ellen</PERSON> the wife of <LOCATION>Nicho</LOCATION>|las <PERSON>Greenliefe</PERSON> of <PERSON>Barton</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, who confessed that three things came to her; one like a Rat, cold and ragged as she felt on him; The next like a <ORGANIZATION>Mole</ORGANIZATION>, soft and cold; The third like a Mouse; and that the <ORGANIZATION>Mole</ORGANIZATION> spoke to her with a great hollow voyce, and asked her to give her soule and body to him, for he could save her, and bad her not be afraid of him, for he could per|forme what he promised, whereupon she consented, then he told her she should never want, but be avenged of all her enemies, and so should continue her life time, if she did not bewray him, for if she did he would have the upper hand of her, and confessed that her wishes came to passe; as for example: she wished one good|man <PERSON>Garneham</PERSON> might be lame, and so he was, and that <PERSON>Master Lockweed</PERSON> might have <ORGANIZATION>Lice</ORGANIZATION>, because he formerly accused her for sending, or causing him to have some when she did it not, and so he had, and that her <ORGANIZATION>Impes</ORGANIZATION> used to suck her two or three times a week, for nineteene yeares together; And that the <ORGANIZATION>Mole</ORGANIZATION> said she should be questioned in some short time, but advised her to stand out and not to confesse, for if she did he would cause her to drowne her selfe, or put her selfe to death, and then he should have her soule, and after when she was kept, before she went to the <MISC>Justices of Peace</MISC>, her <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> in the shape of a <ORGANIZATION>Mole</ORGANIZATION> came to her, when those which were with her saw it not, and tore her as she confessed, as if he would have torne her in pieces, because she had confessed. This woman also confessed, that when she prayed she prayed to the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> and not to <PERSON>God</PERSON>, and that she had her Impes from her mother in Law who she said spoiled her; And further confessed that the <PERSON>Devill</PERSON> had the use of her body, and used to come to bed to her, but was soft, cold, and heavier, so heavie as she could not speake, And that her <PERSON>Impe</PERSON> like a Rat went upon her, wishing to lame <PERSON>Ralph Roggards Horse</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mare</PERSON>, because he said he would goe for the <MISC>Searchers</MISC>, and so it was. Besides the former markes know this, that it is more easi|er to finde them on the brest then in any other place, for that the brest is all shrunke up, and the <LOCATION>Teate</LOCATION> thereof extended longer 29 then any womans that gives suck, be it on man or woman, with a <ORGANIZATION>Circkle</ORGANIZATION> round about it as if it were sucked, and insensible as a|foresaid, and if on a woman that gives suck, that brest is drye, for where the <MISC>Impes</MISC> suck there will come no milke, but the teate will stick out longer there then the other, and is nothing but skinne, and will be much extended as aforesaid, and easily to bee discerned by feeling of it. I should thinke this should give all sa|tisfaction; that gaine, Revenge, feare of want, or poverty, or fearefulnesse of hell torments, or ill parents, or company, yea and lust also, or any one may bee a meanes to draw one to <LOCATION>Witchchraft</LOCATION>.