Witchfinders


A Seventeenth-Century English Tragedy


MALCOLM GASKILL





www.johnmurray.co.uk





First published in <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> in 2008 by <PERSON>John Murray</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Publishers</ORGANIZATION>)

An <ORGANIZATION>Hachette UK Company</ORGANIZATION>

© <PERSON>Malcolm Gaskill</PERSON> 2005

The right of <PERSON>Malcolm Gaskill</PERSON> to be identified as the Author of the Work has been asserted by him in accordance with the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988.


A <ORGANIZATION>CIP</ORGANIZATION> catalogue record for this title is available from the British Library

Epub ISBN: 9781444726923

Book ISBN: 9780719561213

<PERSON>John Murray</PERSON> (Publishers)

338 <LOCATION>Euston Road

London</LOCATION> NW1 3BH

www.johnmurray.co.uk





Contents


Title

Copyright

Dedication

Also by <PERSON>Malcolm Gaskill</PERSON>

Illustrations

Preface

Author’s Note

Map

Prologue


PART ONE: Complication

1. Origins

2. Strange Effects

3. The Initiation

4. Dark Horizons

5. First Blood


PART TWO: Unravelling

6. Malignants

7. Hellish Invention

8. Contagion

9. Sticklers

10. The Biter Bit

Epilogue

Notes

Select Bibliography

Picture Acknowledgements

About the Author





In memory of <PERSON>Stephen Williams</PERSON>

1967–1993

who understood well the strangeness of the past





Also by <PERSON>Malcolm Gaskill</PERSON>

Crime and Mentalities in Early Modern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> (2000)

Hellish Nell: Last of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>’s Witches (2001)





Bear in mind that man is but a devil weakly fettered by some generous beliefs and impositions.

<PERSON>Robert Louis Stevenson</PERSON>

Every tragedy falls into two parts: complication and unravelling … By the complication I mean all that extends from the beginning of the action to the part which marks the turning-point to good or bad fortune. The unravelling is that which extends from the beginning of the change to the end.

<PERSON>Aristotle





Illustrations</PERSON>


‘<PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>, the famous Witch-Finder of Maningtree [sic] in <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>’, c. 1790

The devil in the shape of a headless bear menaces a bed-ridden victim, 1613

A stereotypical witch surrounded by her familiars. A pen-and-ink illustration probably by <PERSON>Miles Gales</PERSON>, rector of <ORGANIZATION>Keighley</ORGANIZATION>, c. 1621–4

Archbishop <PERSON>William Laud</PERSON> depicted as the <PERSON>Antichrist

Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>’ signature on a property conveyance contract, <ORGANIZATION>Ipswich</ORGANIZATION>, 1641

Portrait believed to be of <PERSON>William Dowsing</PERSON>, the ‘Iconoclast General’ (1596–1668)

Witches hanged in <ORGANIZATION>Elizabethan Essex</ORGANIZATION>

An interrogation of suspected witches by King <PERSON>James VI</PERSON> and I (1566–1625)

Parishioners take the Protestation Oath in the presence of their minister, c. 1642

Satan attended by his demonic servants

The witches’ sabbat

<PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> interrogates <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rebecca West

Anne West</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> sinks a boat by witchcraft

Magistrates hear evidence from witnesses

Iconoclasts burn ‘superstitious’ religious pictures, 1643

The devil ministers to his acolytes

The water ordeal inflicted upon a suspected witch, 1613

<PERSON>Robert Rich</PERSON>, 2nd Earl of <ORGANIZATION>Warwick</ORGANIZATION> (1587–1658), Lord High Admiral of the Fleet. Engraving by <PERSON>William Richardson</PERSON>, 1794, after an original by <PERSON>Wenceslaus Hollar</PERSON>, 1642

A mid seventeenth-century witch conjures up demonic spirits

A monstrous birth interpreted as an omen, 1645

The Witch of <LOCATION>Newbury</LOCATION>, 1643

A witch laments the death of Prince <PERSON>Rupert</PERSON>’s dog at <ORGANIZATION>Marston Moor

Edmund Calamy</ORGANIZATION> (1600–66), puritan divine and member of the <ORGANIZATION>Westminster Assembly</ORGANIZATION>. Engraving by <PERSON>James Caldwall</PERSON>, 1775

<PERSON>Samuel Fairclough</PERSON> (1594–1677), rector of <LOCATION>Kedington</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>. Engraving by <PERSON>Frederick Hendrick van Hove</PERSON>, c. 1683

Title-page to A True Relation of the Araignment of eighteene Witches … at <LOCATION>St. Edmunds-bury</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolke</LOCATION>, 1645

A woman is burned at the stake

A mid seventeenth-century execution of convicted witches

A witch feeds her familiars with a spoon

A scold is punished in the ducking-stool

A nation in chaos, 1647

Title-page to <PERSON>John Gaule</PERSON>, Select Cases of Conscience Touching Witches and Witchcrafts, 1646

A parliament of women, 1646

The confession of <PERSON>Margaret Moore</PERSON> of <PERSON>Sutton</PERSON>, May 1647

Title-page to <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>, The Discovery of Witches, 1647

<PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON>’s signed deposition to a magistrate in Ely, July 1647

Title-page to <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON>, A Confirmation and Discovery of Witch-Craft, 1648

Witches worship the devil, cause mayhem, and suffer the consequences, c. 1688

A romantic portrait of <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>, c. 1803–8

For full details of sources and permissions information, see p. 338





Preface


In seventeenth-century <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> people inhabited a magical universe, a cosmos full of spiritual and occult forces with the power to shape earthly events. Not everyone adhered to exactly the same beliefs, nor was there consensus about meaning. And yet a time-traveller would be astonished by the vigorous currents of supernatural thought common to men and women at every social level, from the hub of the metropolis to the darkest corners of the land. Barely fifteen generations ago, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> was a God-fearing but by modern standards superstitious nation, where rivers of Christianity and pagan folklore flowed into one another. The past is always a foreign country, but at times it can feel like an alien world.

In this world, one of the strangest and most pervasive beliefs was that in witchcraft: unseen power, thought by many to be diabolical, harnessed for good and evil ends. Since this idea surely predates written records, and in New Age religion endures today, its historical significance mainly depends on the fact that between 1563 and 1736 witchcraft was a statutory offence punishable by death. Cases varied in character and cause; prosecution levels fluctuated over time and affected different regions in different ways. But <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> experienced only one witch-hunt worthy of the name – a sustained persecution over a wide area, orchestrated by people calling themselves witchfinders. It happened in the counties of <LOCATION>East Anglia</LOCATION> during the civil war of the mid 1640s.

At the centre of this tragedy stand a pair of minor gentlemen, <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON>. How many suspects they interrogated is unknown; there were perhaps three hundred, of whom a third were hanged. Although much of <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>’ life and the witch-hunt he inspired remain obscure, his notoriety has generated many myths. The orthodox version is a fable of wickedness, madness and perversion that banishes ambiguity and passes over unsightly gaps in the record. Yet however distorted this image, the fact remains that two men really did scour eastern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for witches – a story that deserves to be told without recourse to fantasy or fiction. Our seventeenth-century ancestors were mostly decent and intelligent people who could sink to the worst cruelty and credulity at times of intense anxiety. This is a book that reaches beyond monstrous stereotypes to a constituency of unremarkable people, who, through their eager cooperation with <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON>, themselves became witchfinders. In this they resemble the provincial nobodies of the twentieth century who engaged in genocide, demonstrating to the world the banality of evil.



<PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> the witchfinder immortalized. He may have been responsible for the hanging of sixty witches in one year, as this eighteenth-century caption suggests, but it was not in the reign of fames I, nor is there any evidence that he himself was hanged as a wizard

This story had been in my mind for years, but it took film-maker <PERSON>Jonathan Hacker</PERSON> to make me see a book in it. I am grateful to him and to many besides. My agent <PERSON>Felicity Bryan</PERSON> has supported me throughout, and at <PERSON>John Murray Roland Philipps</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rowan Yapp</PERSON> have been enthusiastic and efficient. My diligent copy editor <PERSON>Liz Robinson</PERSON> made many valuable improvements to the text, as did <PERSON>Adam Lively</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ros Roughton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sheena Peirse</PERSON>. <PERSON>Sheena</PERSON> arranged a stay in the haunted ‘Witchfinder Suite’ at the <LOCATION>Thorn Hotel</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION> – an unforgettable experience. <PERSON>Patrick Goodbody</PERSON> kindly invited me to his house at <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION>, once home to the <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> family. Acknowledgement is also due to the staff of the <ORGANIZATION>Public Record Office</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House of Lords Record Office</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>British Library</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University Library</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Bodleian Library</ORGANIZATION>, Dr <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>’s Library, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> Plume’s Library, the <ORGANIZATION>Pepysian Library at Magdalene College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, and the county record offices at <LOCATION>Bedford</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Bury St Edmunds</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colchester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hertford</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Huntingdon</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ipswich</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>King</ORGANIZATION>’s <PERSON>Lynn</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Northampton</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norwich</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Harwich Town Council</ORGANIZATION> also generously granted me access to their archives.

Historians who have shared their time and research include <PERSON>Frank Bremer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Peter Elmer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carolyn Fox</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ronald Hutton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mark Lawrence</PERSON>, <PERSON>Diarmaid MacCulloch</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Morrill</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keith Parry</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jim Sharpe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alex Shepard</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Heide Towers</ORGANIZATION>. I am most indebted to <PERSON>Robin Briggs</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ivan Bunn</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Walter</PERSON> for commenting on an early draft. I would also like to thank the <ORGANIZATION>Arts and Humanities Research Board</ORGANIZATION> for funding sabbatical leave, likewise the Master and Fellows of <ORGANIZATION>Churchill College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> for their indulgence.

If <PERSON>Robert Louis Stevenson</PERSON> was right, and man really is but a devil weakly fettered, I can only say that the generous beliefs and impositions of all those mentioned here have mattered more.





Author’s Note


Seventeenth-century <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> had yet to convert from the <PERSON>Julian</PERSON> to the Gregorian calendar. This meant that the New Year began on 25 March. To avoid confusion, I have rendered all Old Style dates as New Style, with the year starting on 1 January.

Original spelling has been kept for quotations, although punctuation has been modified to improve the sense of certain passages. As even within the same document the spelling of names tended to be erratic, these have been standardized for the sake of consistency.





Prologue




THE CHRISTMAS OF 1644 was a joyless time in the <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>. Easterly gales funnelled down the <LOCATION>Stour</LOCATION> estuary, the river froze an iron grey, and snow drifted high against the warehouses. In the lanes leading up from the harbour the poor fretted over dwindling stocks of food and fuel, and at the waning of each pale sun huddled round fires, relishing their pottage and bread. At least in previous winters there had been festive cheer and revels. But now, throughout <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, not only had the puritan authorities denounced celebrations as superstitious, but Christmas Day coincided with a compulsory public fast.1 Unthanked in church for the <LOCATION>Saviour</LOCATION>’s birth, God heard only the usual prayers that the old and frail, the young and the sick, and soldiers still fighting the war between king and <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, should be spared their lives until the blessed release of spring.

Least joyous of all, and most earnest in his prayers, was <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON>, a tailor whose house stood on a hill off the high street. This winter he had little time for his patterns and fabrics, and customers wanting coats and capes could wait: his wife had been struck down by an all-consuming fever which now threatened her life. At first she had complained of dizziness and nausea but soon was confined to bed, her body flushing hot and cold, her senses dulled. As <PERSON>Rivet</PERSON> watched this suffering, his petitions to heaven unanswered, he wondered why God should treat his wife so cruelly, and so began to suspect that her condition was caused by ‘something more then meerly naturall’.2

In the coming days, <ORGANIZATION>Goodwife Rivet</ORGANIZATION>’s condition worsened. To lameness and delirium were added muscular tremors which increased in intensity until her body shook and contorted, finally convincing her husband that this affliction had no earthly cause. From the unnatural times in which they lived, such things might even have been expected. These were ‘days of shaking’ – of rebellion and fighting, of uncertainty, fear and grief; the orderly world created and governed by heaven was being turned upside-down. Fair was foul, and foul was fair. That year, brother had slain brother; <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> had ruled without a king; harvests had spoiled in the fields while folk went hungry; and plagues and agues had touched high and low with a fickle hand. The devil reigned. ‘If Witches and <ORGANIZATION>Wizards</ORGANIZATION> have any power in their black Art,’ a preacher warned the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION>, ‘now is a time for them to drive a full trade … either for love or money, for feare, hopes, or hatred.’3

Like Rivet’s wife, the entire nation seemed to be in the grip of an incurable malady, leading people to believe that a wrathful God demanded repentence or retribution. In havens of piety like <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> and the adjacent port of <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>, these were seen as the last days of man before <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>’s final decisive battle with Satan, for behind the cannon-fire and cavalry charges raged an ideological war, as much spiritual as political in its passions. Calvinists at <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION> were busy sweeping away the religious innovations of the 1630s, which were seen as popish and idolatrous, and had confined their chief architect, Archbishop <PERSON>William Laud</PERSON>, to the Tower of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. The fever of change was infectious. <ORGANIZATION>Across Essex</ORGANIZATION> and eastern <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> puritans, supported by crowds drunk on chaos, unleashed righteous anger upon Catholics, Laudian ceremonies, and church decorations. To the reformers, Laudianism – much like the rituals of folk religion – was little better than diabolical magic.

But it was hard to shun superstition with Death peering through the window. A fortnight of prayer having brought neither reason nor remedy, <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON> decided on an unlawful action to end his wife’s torment. He set off for Hadleigh in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, a depressed cloth town across the river <LOCATION>Stour</LOCATION>, where he sought out <PERSON>Goodwife Hovey</PERSON>, a woman famed for her skill in healing and divination. Cunning folk such as she were popular but proscribed; the authorities taught that they were evil charlatans, deluded into believing they dispensed God’s power. In fact, parish ministers and the ecclesiastical courts had long insisted that in theory they were witches. Yet to <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON>’s thinking, a witch was a hag who visited disaster upon her enemies, the sort of wretch who was trying to kill his wife.

There is no record of <PERSON>Hovey</PERSON>’s methods; perhaps she boiled Goodwife Rivet’s urine and hair in a stone bottle – a common diagnostic spell. By some magical means she confirmed <PERSON>Rivet</PERSON>’s suspicion that his wife was bewitched, and suggested that a Manningtree woman up the hill from him was the cause of woe in his household. Without hesitation Rivet identified <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>, an aged one-legged widow who lived alone, dependent on parish charity. It was common knowledge, he said, that ‘<PERSON>Elizabeths</PERSON> mother and some other of her kinsfolke did suffer death for Witchcraft and murther’.4 As a legacy of this shame it is likely she had been a marked figure all her life, reviled but perhaps also revered among her watchful neighbours.

The witchery in Widow <PERSON>Clarke</PERSON>’s blood seemed plain enough, but usually it took many years for the pressure of suspicion to build before it exploded into an accusation. Even then a witch-trial was a risky undertaking: costly in time and money, and liable to backfire if the defendant was acquitted. For a prosecution to gain momentum, plaintiffs had to be unusually confident or foolhardy, or unusually afraid or angry.5 <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON> was certainly the latter, and did not hesitate to broadcast his convictions at his return. Word spread quickly through the gossip networks of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>, and so reached the ears of a callow, vainglorious gentleman named <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>.

For a younger son of a clergyman, whose life so far had held few ambitions or adventures, the news was electrifying. At last <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> sensed a mission, a chance to make his mark. According to a contemporary portrait he wore his beard short, but his hair long over a broad linen collar. The high-crowned hat, <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> cape and bucket-top boots suggest that he affected the style of a country magistrate, his staff and spurs self-importance rather than real authority. He kept a greyhound that accompanied him around the town.6 Although it is easy to imagine that <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> was sly and sarcastic, there is no reason to think him insincere in his convictions: a Calvinist belief in his own predestined salvation, and a loathing of witchcraft and idolatry as cancers at the heart of Christian society. And so, <PERSON>Rivet</PERSON>’s accusation of old <PERSON>Bess Clarke</PERSON> focused his mind.

Not that <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> lacked first-hand experience of witches – or so he said. For some time now, once every six weeks or so and always on a Friday night, he had been disturbed by eerie voices drifting over the fields near his house. Standing at his bedchamber window, pressing an ear to the darkness and hardly daring to breathe, he had caught snatches of conversation between the witches of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> and their accomplices from neighbouring villages. Gatherings known as sabbats, where witches met to worship the devil and devise malevolent plots, had long been recorded by <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> inquisitors; but they were rarely heard of in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, where most people thought that communion with Satan was achieved through familiar spirits, or imps, disguised as animals. Convinced that the witches had detected his spying, <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> later claimed they had despatched a bear-like spirit to kill him, but that he had been protected by the carapace of his godliness. He added that the coven had commanded some imps to assist a particular witch living in Manningtree: the name he overheard was that of an old widow, <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>.7



<PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>’ claim that a bear-like spirit had been sent to kill him may have been inspired by a number of stories in circulation, such as that recounted in this pamphlet of 1613

It is tempting to move to the bizarre climax of this episode, the catalytic moment in the tragic witch-hunt that was to follow. But, as if winter had frozen the matter of the witches pending the arrival of spring, this did not take place until March 1645. Only then did old hatreds thaw out, allowing a plan to germinate and grow. Suffice it to say that the suffering about to be inflicted upon <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON> would unite <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON>, another Manningtree gentleman, and that together they would swear to have witnessed the ultimate display of a witch’s depravity: a parade of offspring fathered by the devil himself. It was this shocking encounter which would set <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> inexorably on the road to experience, and unrivalled expertise, as witchfinders.8





PART ONE


Complication





1


Origins




ONE DAY LATE in the reign of <PERSON>James</PERSON> I a crisis at the rectory of <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> was reaching its peak. It was a trial endured by most women several times in their lives, but every occasion brought the same dread, pain and peril. The rector’s wife was confined in an upstairs chamber, the bed surrounded by ‘godsiblings’ – her dearest female friends and relations. A drink of warm spiced ale, known as caudle, may have been held to her lips; a scented cloth mopped sweat from her brow. In this, <LOCATION>Wenham</LOCATION>’s most godly household, prayers were said to keep Satan at bay, protecting the defenceless woman as her body and soul travelled between sacred states. <PERSON>Mary Hopkins</PERSON> was about to complete her labour, and would soon be delivered of a baby boy.

Like all puritans immersed in Holy Scripture, <PERSON>Mary Hopkins</PERSON> would have known of God’s sentence upon Eve: ‘I will greatly multiply thy sorrow … in sorrow thou shalt bring forth children.’ Because of this, women endured the agonies of childbirth like a penance, and accepted heaven’s judgement whenever offspring were taken from them. This was <PERSON>Mary</PERSON>’s fourth baby to survive; she may have borne others less fortunate. But for the moment at least this boy, like his three brothers before him, grasped life, and <PERSON>God</PERSON> was content. The midwife severed the cord, and the child was washed and wrapped up warmly. The mother then rested while the women busied themselves in the chamber, stoking the fire and drying linen. The greatest danger had passed, a moment marked by prayers of gratitude. <PERSON>Mary</PERSON>’s confinement probably continued for another month, during which time her godsiblings served her as lying-in maids.1 Meanwhile her husband <PERSON>James</PERSON> was preparing to protect his son from the malign influence of the spiritual world.

In the previous century the English state had thrown off the authority of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> to establish a <ORGANIZATION>Protestant</ORGANIZATION> national Church. Consensus had been elusive: reform went too far for some, for others not far enough. Catholics believed the Reformation should not have happened at all, and under Queen <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> they rejoiced as the clocks were turned back. Protestants refusing to recant were burned, then memorialized as martyrs in the reign of <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> I, who restored the reformed faith. Yet the Elizabethan settlement was a fudged compromise, with many Catholic traditions preserved and codified in the Book of Common Prayer. Clergy continued to be ordained by bishops, themselves empowered by the monarch’s divine right; images of saints still adorned parish churches; communicants swallowed bread and wine, even if officially it was no longer the actual body and blood of <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>. Outrage at what were seen as popish survivals stoked the fires of puritanism: a poorly defined Calvinist tendency towards dissatisfaction with the theology and liturgy of the Church of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, and a boundless appetite for the Bible and its moral lessons. Puritans – or ‘the godly’, as they called themselves – wanted a simplified religion based on Scripture and nothing else.2

It was not enough that the meanings of images and rituals had been changed – for example, that communion had been downgraded from a miracle to a mere remembrance. Puritans argued that the practices themselves originated with <PERSON>Antichrist</PERSON>, and that in any case the uneducated failed to distinguish between the symbolic and the real. <PERSON>Churching</PERSON> was a case in point. Once the ritual purification of a new mother, after the Reformation churching became a simple act of thanksgiving; but for the majority it remained a pagan defence against the dangers of life’s transitions. Godly clergy tried to satisfy the law and their own consciences by performing these ceremonies in an understated way, consoled by the thought that God alone could determine the effects of their ministry on the congregation. In this way a puritan like <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> might have churched his own wife with only mild discomfort, provided that she did not wear a veil or kneel at the altar.3

Where life and death were concerned, almost everyone was prone to superstition. It was said that a pregnant woman who gazed at the moon risked her child’s sanity; a taste for red berries was thought to cause blemishes; and birth defects were linked to contact with animals. The herbs, charms and holy relics that before the Reformation had sanctified the birthing-chamber may have been easily banished, but the perception of proximate evil lingered on; even puritans succumbed to the temptation to protect themselves. Despite the abolition of saints, furtive supplications were made to <LOCATION>St Margaret</LOCATION> to alleviate birth pangs, and to <LOCATION>St Felicitas</LOCATION> to ensure the baby was a boy. Some went further: reassurance was sought from astrologers and cunning folk by people either unaware of the impiety of the act, or able to persuade themselves that it was permitted by God.4

Of all rituals surrounding childbirth, baptism stirred up most controversy. For radical Protestants, the christening of infants made a conjuror of the minister; and yet not only did the ceremony have by law to be performed but most parents demanded it, craving the peace of mind it brought. Again, whether the ritual constituted an actual spiritual transformation or just a public display depended on individual perception, though on this point, silent compromise between minister and congregation could not always be reached. Parents attached great importance to the minister making the sign of the cross on the child’s head, and this was where puritan clergymen drew the line. Struggling to balance conviction with obligation, many refused to complete the sacrament as some parishioners desired. If they were lucky, they merely caused scandal; but they might also be summoned to an ecclesiastical court to explain themselves.

However <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> coped with the dilemma, at some point between his wife’s lying-in and her churching he baptized their son into the <ORGANIZATION>Christian Church</ORGANIZATION> at the ancient font of <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION> for all the parish to see. <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> (or the men he had chosen to be godfathers) had named his other sons <PERSON>James</PERSON>, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> and <PERSON>John</PERSON> after the Apostles, hopeful that God’s power and determination to fight evil would be bestowed upon them, as recorded in the <ORGANIZATION>Gospels</ORGANIZATION>. Like his brothers, this boy was christened to symbolize a life-long devotion to <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> as mentor, guide, guardian and saviour: he was named <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON>.5

*

Until the age of about five, infants remained extremely vulnerable to illness and disease. Contrary to modern myth, mothers took great care to preserve their children’s lives, and grieved bitterly if they failed. To extend the security of the womb and straighten a growing body, many babies were swaddled for the first weeks of life. Washing was a secondary priority, and cradle-cap was often left untreated until the bones of the skull had fused. Mothers trimmed a baby’s nails with their teeth (it was believed that unmanicured children were more likely to become thieves) and the trimmings were burned or buried. Suspended between the animate and the inanimate, such human waste was ambiguous matter – raw material for witches, who were believed to turn traces of life back against the body of origin. Children, too young to protect themselves by faith, prayer or charm, were at greatest risk.

Breast-feeding was thought to encourage the child’s development, especially when it was feared that cow’s milk might infect the child with bestial qualities. In a well-to-do household like that of <PERSON>James</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Hopkins</PERSON>, it is possible that <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> was breast-fed by a wet-nurse. Most children were weaned at about a year, and teething was seen as an unavoidable phase of illness. An infusion of poppies was a customary pacifier, and suffering children were given a piece of coral to suck – it was also a charm against witches.6 The growing infant was now exposed to an environment where contact between humans and animals was commonplace, and the separation of sewage and water supply imperfect. Diarrhoea claimed many infant lives, and infestations of threadworm impeded weight-gain. Herbal remedies ranged in effectiveness from the benign and useless to the poisonous and fatal. Most feared were smallpox, diphtheria, scarlet fever, typhoid and, worst of all, bubonic plague, against which only prayer, fasting and public humiliation might prove effective.

Discipline was strict, but beatings rare. Ideally, order in the family was promoted through love of God and mutual respect, as defined by patriarchal convention. Experience of the holy household – a microcosm of the state – provided the basic influences <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> would have needed to meet the expectations of his elders. Play was important too, although some puritans preferred to use the time drilling their offspring in the habit of secret prayer.7 At the fireside or in the company of friends, children soaked up stories, and not just improving fables but winter’s tales about ghosts and witches, which invaded their dreams and shaped their perceptions. Where parents disapproved, a nurse was usually a reliable source of folklore. Children believed that backyards, gardens and the fields near their homes were infested with fairies and imps as real as mice and bugs; by searching for such creatures, and placating them with flowers and morsels, they developed a fear of the unseen world, and at the same time a fascination with its mysteries. By the time young <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> came to hear his first sermon, his consciousness had already straddled the blurry borderland between natural and supernatural realms.

Another influence on his development was the mounting tension in public life which in 1642 resulted in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>’s worst political crisis since the Wars of the Roses. The attitudes of the juvenile <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> must have been deeply affected by the impact of <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> I’s policies upon his own <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> community, especially in view of his father’s pivotal role. Surely he overheard anguished voices at the rectory complaining no longer just that godly reformation had stalled, but that it was going backwards. It was a grievance to which <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> was entirely sympathetic. Those men and women who believed themselves to be the elect – the saved already chosen by God – would have to fight to justify their special status. To walk the hard road ahead, it would be insufficient for <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>’ sons merely to follow <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> in their hearts: they would have to demonstrate their devotion by public intervention and the setting of examples.8

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> hailed from <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION> in the Isle of Ely, the fenland north of <LOCATION>Cambridgeshire</LOCATION>. Situated on a hill by the river <LOCATION>Great Ouse</LOCATION>, the town was surrounded by water for much of the year, and even during the dry season was cut off by a broad mere, by tradition the colour of blood. Strong mint, used to pack smoked mutton in winter, grew around its banks where a monstrous wild dog was said to stalk the unwary.9 As the name suggested the manor of <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION> had once sustained a busy port, and it had belonged to the Bishop of <PERSON>Ely</PERSON> until the Reformation, when it passed into the hands of yeoman farmers. Throughout <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, such men then exploited soaring food prices by enclosing common land – land on which the poor depended – to make it more profitable, and so recast themselves as gentlemen.



An impoverished witch surrounded by a menagerie of animal familiars. By 1621, when this drawing was made, the stereotype was fixed in most people’s minds

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON>’ father <PERSON>William</PERSON> was one of these. He married in about 1560 and raised two sons, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <PERSON>William</PERSON>. <PERSON>Robert</PERSON>, the eldest, was sent to <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> in the mid 1570s, around which time his mother died and his father married <PERSON>Martha Saunders</PERSON>; she gave birth to <PERSON>James</PERSON> and to two daughters, <PERSON>Martha</PERSON> and <PERSON>Anne</PERSON>. By now <PERSON>William Hopkins</PERSON> was a landowner of substance who had built a house and owned several others, as well as fields, crofts and fishing waters. He was one of twelve worthies chosen to administer property belonging to the royal manor of <LOCATION>East Greenwich</LOCATION>, the rents from which were put to charitable ends. In his will <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> pledged a cow to the parish poor, perhaps to expiate a feeling of guilt for having taken their land.10

When <PERSON>William Hopkins</PERSON> died in 1583 his widow <PERSON>Martha</PERSON> was named as his executrix, and the recipient of his main residence and lands. His eldest son <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> received most of the estate, plus his father’s gold ring and an annuity of £ 5. The second largest share went to <PERSON>William</PERSON>, and the daughters were well cared for too. Of the sons, <PERSON>James</PERSON>, who can have been little more than a baby, received least, but even so was bequeathed three houses, a parcel of copyhold land, a croft, two feather-beds, a chestful of linen, three fine silver Apostle spoons, and £ 20, all to be held in trust until his twenty-second birthday. Moreover, he was named principal heir should his half-brother <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> die without issue. <PERSON>Robert Hopkins</PERSON>, who after leaving <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> instructed godless inmates in a house of correction, died four years later; but whether he married and had children is unknown. It is possible that the infant <PERSON>James</PERSON> became wealthy before the age of seven.

In 1597, when he was about fifteen, <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> was awarded a Perne scholarship at Peterhouse, <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University</ORGANIZATION>’s oldest college.11 By that time, he probably knew he was destined to enter the <ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION>. His inheritance would make even the meanest stipend bearable, and his finances were about to improve yet further. His widowed mother had moved from <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION> to the city of Ely, to be closer to her daughters. She died in December 1600, leaving most of her estate not to her stepson <PERSON>William</PERSON> but to <PERSON>James</PERSON>, her own flesh and blood, who in addition to £25, a great deal of furniture and another three Apostle spoons was invested with what she termed ‘all my right and title in that p[ar]te of the Manor of <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION> w[hi]ch I now injoye’. She favoured <PERSON>James</PERSON>, she explained, ‘because I repose an extraordinarie trust & creadite in hym above others that he wilbe readie as nede shalbe to releave the great wantes w[hi]ch I heare will fall uppon his Sister <PERSON>Martha</PERSON>’. The younger <PERSON>Martha Hopkins</PERSON> had married, but why she should have needed protection remains obscure. What is striking is the evidence that <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> was already displaying the sort of personal qualities that later enabled him to lead a <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> congregation during its most testing times, and to impart a sense of Christian duty to his children.12

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> was admitted as Bachelor of Arts in the year after his mother died and elected into a Fellowship around the time of his twenty-second birthday, when he also received his inheritance. He was still at Peterhouse in 1608, and the following year was ordained at Ely Cathedral; his marriage took place soon afterwards. In 1612 he was presented to the living of <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION>, a secluded parish of 1,000 acres and perhaps a hundred souls, and took his wife <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> to live there in the timber-framed rectory opposite the church.13 It seems they also took with them a servant, possibly a sister-in-law of <PERSON>James</PERSON>’s sister <PERSON>Martha</PERSON>. Within four years <PERSON>James</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> had been blessed with three sons: <PERSON>James</PERSON>, the first-born, followed by <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> and <PERSON>John</PERSON>.14 <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> must have sold off his land in <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION>, as he was not mentioned in a lawsuit at the <ORGANIZATION>Court of Chancery</ORGANIZATION> in 1613 by which poor tenants fought to defend their rights of common against the <PERSON>Peyton</PERSON> family, now sole lords of the manor of <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION>.15 From the sale of this land or by some other means <PERSON>James</PERSON> acquired land thirty miles from <LOCATION>Littleport</LOCATION>, at <LOCATION>Framlingham Castle</LOCATION> – a location that later had a sinister significance for his son <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON>.16

The faith that <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> acquired in childhood provided his moral, emotional and intellectual compass later on. The phrasing of his grandparents’ wills suggests Protestant conformity, if not enthusiastic godliness, and the fact that his father and uncle had entered the Church is significant. Puritan dissenters were strong in <LOCATION>Cambridgeshire</LOCATION> from the reign of <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, ranging from moderate Calvinists to Anabaptists with heretical opinions about souls and sacraments.17 As compared with the beliefs of the majority, however, the similarities between these sects surpassed the differences. In the 1580s <PERSON>Richard Greenham</PERSON>, rector of Dry <PERSON>Drayton</PERSON> near <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, had toiled to build a godly community, but found the people ignorant and refractory. The Reformation had turned clergymen from miracle-workers into mere spiritual counsellors, and among husbandmen faced with crop failure and disease there was no question which sort of ministry was most valuable. In the end <LOCATION>Greenham</LOCATION> admitted defeat, blaming rampant superstition and his parishioners’ tendency to hold witches responsible for their misfortunes rather than searching their own sinful hearts and praying for guidance.18

Eventually many ministers confined their preaching to the converted, and ignored the rest. Not that this attitude entirely conflicted with God’s plan, at least in the view of strict Calvinists, who believed that the division of the world into the damned and the saved was predetermined. For them, godliness and good works were neither an effort of will nor a means of salvation, but a natural extension of their innate being. In the first decade of the seventeenth century, when <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> was teaching at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, he was surrounded by men who passionately avowed this doctrine; and there is every reason to believe that he was one of them. It was at this time that the king, <PERSON>James</PERSON> I, entrusted the learned doctors of the <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> with the translation of a new English Bible. When he arrived in <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION> in 1612 <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> doubtless carried with him a copy of the new Authorized Version. In print for just a year at that time, in his lifetime it became the foundation of Protestant teaching and thinking, and remained so forever after.

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON>’ experience at <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION> probably did not differ greatly from that of <LOCATION>Richard Greenham</LOCATION> at Dry Drayton thirty years earlier. There were those who could not or would not hear the word of God, plus the usual scattering of tipplers and profaners, rogues and bastard-bearers, cunning folk and their clients. The devil was in every place. In his quest for order it was helpful to <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> that the lord of the manor was a devout puritan, unlike other <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> parishes where the gentry were lacklustre Protestants or even <ORGANIZATION>Catholic</ORGANIZATION> recusants. Great <LOCATION>Wenham</LOCATION> also benefited from its proximity to <LOCATION>Dedham Vale</LOCATION>, a region distinguished by energetic godliness, and early in his ministry <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> became well acquainted with preachers and pious laymen from here and throughout the <LOCATION>Stour valley</LOCATION>. Powerful dynasties such as the Bacons and the <PERSON>Barnardistons</PERSON> offered patronage and hospitality to men like <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> as they journeyed from place to place, sharing their learning and stiffening people’s resolve. In a sea of hostility and indifference, these communities were islands of piety, amity and hope.19

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON>’ first line of defence was his own household. On top of the sermons they heard and the catechisms they were set, <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> and his brothers were directed by their father in study, contemplation and prayer, and had drummed into them an understanding of their election. They would have learnt their letters locally before progressing to grammar school, possibly in the nearby towns of <LOCATION>Ipswich</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Colchester</LOCATION>, where the Latin and Greek necessary to enter a university were taught.

By this time <PERSON>King James</PERSON> had been succeeded by his son <PERSON>Charles</PERSON>, a man more refined than his father but less politically astute. <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> exalted God, but scarcely less did he exalt his own high office, thereby blinding himself to his responsibility to <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. In 1629, to satisfy his financial and religious ambitions, he had declared himself an absolute monarch. Among his aims was the introduction of a less austere form of Protestantism that would restore the ornament and ceremony of pre-Reformation days. To this end, he promoted to the episcopal bench clerics who favoured the anti-Calvinist teachings of the Dutch theologian <PERSON>Arminius</PERSON>, emphasizing free grace for all and opposing the idea of predestination. This was a serious affront to the puritan communities of the <LOCATION>Stour valley</LOCATION> and beyond: all that they held pure would be desecrated, their work undone. As a young man, <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> no doubt remembered his father’s outrage at these innovations, a sentiment shared by all their godly friends. To them, it was as if idolatry and sorcery were being reinstalled at the heart of English life. If there was one aspect of his childhood more likely than any other to have initiated and inspired <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON>’s career as a witchfinder, this was it.

In 1633, by which time <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> had reached adolescence, <PERSON>William Laud</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bishop</PERSON> of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, was appointed to the See of <LOCATION>Canterbury</LOCATION>. A committed advocate of ‘the beauty of holiness’ in worship and a stickler for Anglican uniformity, he became the focus of godly resentment and disgust. Although neither the Arminian nor the closet Catholic his enemies painted him, he refused to tolerate disobedience on the part of puritan clergy. Unsurprisingly <PERSON>Matthew Wren</PERSON>, the Bishop of <LOCATION>Norwich</LOCATION>, in whose diocese most <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> puritans lived, shared his new archbishop’s views. It was not long before the Church’s courts were routinely censuring ministers for refusing to make the sign of the cross during baptism, and numerous other abuses of the liturgy. Mere admonition was soon deemed inadequate, and the punishment was increased to dismissal.20



Archbishop <PERSON>Laud</PERSON> depicted as the <LOCATION>Antichrist</LOCATION>, accepting tithes from one man and popish trinkets from another. He has the Number of the Beast inscribed on his forehead

<PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> must have experienced despair and anger, feelings which may have contributed to the decline of his health by 1634. It is easy to imagine the pessimism he would have felt for his eldest son as he took his bachelor’s degree at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> that year and prepared to enter the ministry. The younger <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> had been sent not to his father’s Peterhouse but to <ORGANIZATION>Emmanuel College</ORGANIZATION>, the puritan nursery which had so far produced the finest foot-soldiers of godly reform.21 But now the Church was in turmoil, and hopes began to fade. So far had matters deteriorated that even conformist clergy opposed the Arminian bishops, not least because of the draconian judgments handed down by the ecclesiastical courts. Puritans experienced Laud’s reforms as nothing less than orchestrated persecution, and although the more stoical may have been energized by oppression, for the rest the dream of building <LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION> in the land of their birth was over. The only option was emigration to <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>.22

Those who had done so wrote to their <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> friends, firing their imaginations, filling them with longing for a promised land. In 1630 <PERSON>John Winthrop</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> clothier destined to be the first governor of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, left the village of <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION>, twelve miles from <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION>; his intention was ‘to avoid the burthens and snares which were here laid upon their consciences’.23 Among the friends he left behind was <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON>, from whom a letter of praise and encouragement survives. Sent to <PERSON>Winthrop</PERSON> in February 1633, this torn page speaks volumes about <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>’ character, and the combative stance he passed on to his famous son. In language steeped in biblical allusion and a sense of divine providence, <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON> admires the challenges presented by <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, and even expresses satisfaction that <PERSON>Winthrop</PERSON> should have enemies, as this only proved his worthiness. ‘The magistrate beinge the minister of god for the upholdinge of the good, and punishinge and suppression of the badd,’ he commented, ‘must needes have wicked mens mouthes open against him, as good ones will speak for him.’24

To <PERSON>James Hopkins</PERSON>, the opposition of virtue and evil was visible in all things. <PERSON>Winthrop</PERSON>’s honour he contrasted with the actions of ‘heathens [and p]apists whoe have taken great paines to fill the [nation?] with sup[erstiti]on and wickednes’. <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> had grown weak, he admitted, and drifted in thought from his <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> rectory to the shores of <LOCATION>Massachusetts Bay</LOCATION>. Praying for guidance, he told <PERSON>Winthrop</PERSON>: ‘I have a purpose to make my selfe a member of your plantation, and when I come, I hope I shall not come alone.’ But by the winter of 1634 <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> was confined to bed, and there his dreams evaporated. He dictated his will, made his peace with God, and in January 1635 he died. <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> was probably no more than fourteen, and had no special place in his father’s plans. His eldest brother <PERSON>James</PERSON>, still at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> studying to become Master of Arts, received all his father’s books, to assist him in his career as a minister; the second son, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON>, was to be sent away ‘ov[er] the seaes to such our frinds in <LOCATION>Newe England</LOCATION>’. What had eluded the father, it seemed, the sons were exhorted to achieve, and although <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> received no formal instructions, when the time came he knew what he had to do.25

Between 1638 and 1642 <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> slid into chaos. Attempts to impose the Arminian Prayer Book in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> precipitated a Calvinist rebellion, forcing King <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> to call the first <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> for eleven years in order to raise money for the defence of his crown. He met stiff opposition from lawyers guarding the constitution, and from English Presbyterians sympathetic to the Scots. The next two years saw the king driven into a corner, his allies impeached, his authority restricted, and his subjects across the three kingdoms thrown into rebellious turmoil. After many years of fretfulness, at last godly activists caught the scent of victory. In 1641 a puritan zealot named <PERSON>Lewis Hughes</PERSON> published a tract attacking the ‘blasphemies and lying fables’ of the Book of Common Prayer, including the superstitious churching of women: this, he asserted, transformed the officiating minister into a kind of witch.26 In an age when politics and religion were two sides of the same coin this was fighting talk, and there was plenty more besides. In the spring of 1642 <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> fled <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, his <ORGANIZATION>Catholic</ORGANIZATION> wife <PERSON>Henrietta Maria</PERSON> sailed for the Continent, and <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> passed the <ORGANIZATION>Militia Ordinance</ORGANIZATION> passing military power to the lords lieutenant in the shires. By the summer, both sides were recruiting and equipping armies.

In August <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> raised his standard at <LOCATION>Nottingham</LOCATION>, branding his opponents ‘rebels’ in response to <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>’s declaration that royalists were ‘traitors’. The battle-lines were ideological, even metaphysical, the fighting thought to mirror the conflicts of the celestial sphere, where <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> would vanquish the forces of evil. It was easy for one side to accuse the other of diabolical inspiration; but whereas the language of most royalist propaganda was figurative, that of their enemies was more literal. For puritans these really were the last days of mankind, the war was an actual prologue to Armageddon, and the king was a real agent of <PERSON>Antichrist</PERSON>. Among the men who had resisted the king most aggressively in <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> – and who now were most active in organizing troops – were the strictest Calvinists, who had been fighting for further reformation of religion long before the first musket was fired in 1642.27

In the streets, terrifying stories of judgements and omens were on everyone’s lips. A cavalier in <LOCATION>Cornwall</LOCATION> drank a health to Satan and was driven insane. In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the devil appeared at a secret meeting of Jesuits, ‘all as black as pitch, as bigge as a great Dogge’. On the banks of the Thames the cry went up that a witch had been seen walking on the water, and tidal waves were interpreted by the watermen as ‘Newes from Heaven’ – a warning to the nation. The truth of ancient prophecies seemed confirmed. In 1642 a sea-monster, described as ‘the devill in the shape of a great fish’, was put on display in <ORGANIZATION>Woolwich</ORGANIZATION>, an example of ‘the fore-runners and sad harbingers of great commotions and tumults in <LOCATION>States</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Kingdomes</PERSON>, if not mournfull Heraulds of utter desolation’.28 Royalist propagandists exploited the story of a puritan woman in <ORGANIZATION>Northamptonshire</ORGANIZATION> who announced that she would prefer her child to be born headless than to have it baptized with the sign of the cross, only for her terrible wish to be granted.29 Visions of armies were seen in the skies, and the phantom sounds of battle were heard around <LOCATION>Edgehill</LOCATION> and elsewhere.30

To the godly, these omens meant one thing: they were about to live through the Second Coming, prior to being invested as <PERSON>Christ</PERSON>’s saints. Meanwhile, opportunities for them to justify their election were legion, from extemporary preaching on street corners to training with a company of pikemen. If indeed <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> had planned to go to <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> and these plans had been scuppered by the outbreak of war, surely these were the compensations. His father’s dying wish had been only that <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> and his siblings should be educated to the highest standard possible, ‘and that they may be brought up in the feare of God & in such honest callings as shall best suite w[i]th there disposicions & eastates’. Why <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON> did not follow his father, uncle and brother to <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> and into the <ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION> will never be known. The family could have afforded it. As well as the estate left to <PERSON>Matthew</PERSON>’s mother, the six children each received a legacy of a hundred marks (equivalent to perhaps £70,000 today), to be held in trust until they reached the age of twenty-two, not to mention various properties.31 But in an age of religious uncertainty, a commercial apprenticeship perhaps held more appeal than a clerical career. Legend has it that while still an adolescent <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> found an opening as some kind of lawyer’s clerk based in <LOCATION>Ipswich</LOCATION>, but the evidence is flimsy in the extreme.32



Only one of <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>’ signatures is known to survive, here on a conveyance document from 1641 – virtually all there is to substantiate the claim that he was a lawyer

The civil war brought chaos, but to someone like <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> it offered exhilaration, and vindication too. <PERSON>Bishop Wren</PERSON> had persecuted preachers of ‘new and strange’ doctrine but now the positions were reversed and so-called ‘scandalous’ clergymen, like the <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION> minister who had denigrated ‘Spirit-mongers, Puritans, & People of phanaticall Spirits’, were ejected from their livings.33 Among other grievances against the Laudian clergy were excessive drinking, profaning the Sabbath, molesting female parishioners, and persuading men not to fight for <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.34 But what the godly most appreciated was not having to watch a minister bow to the altar or make the sign of the cross.

To most people, church decorations were fragments of heaven on earth. To reformers they were false idols, inventions of <PERSON>Antichrist</PERSON> that contravened the second commandment and imperilled the soul, and as such had been under attack even before war broke out. ‘Idolatry is the principall crime of mankinde,’ a polemicist wrote in 1641, ‘the greatest guilt of the world, the totall cause of judgement’; stained-glass windows he lumped in with astrology, magic and witchcraft.35 In that year, <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> had ordered the destruction of altar rails, candlesticks and crucifixes; spontaneous outbursts of iconoclasm followed. Catholics were attacked and their property destroyed, according to one observer, ‘as if there had been a dissolution of all government’.36 Naturally the authorities preferred a more orderly purge. By 1643 the puritan <PERSON>Earl</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> – Captain-General of the army in <LOCATION>East Anglia</LOCATION> – was using money sequestered from royalists to fund the religious revolution; agents working for <ORGANIZATION>Parliament’s Committee for Scandalous Ministers</ORGANIZATION> each received five shillings a day.37 <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> also commissioned <PERSON>William Dowsing</PERSON>, a farmer from <ORGANIZATION>Stratford St Mary</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Dedham Vale</LOCATION>, to tour the churches of the eastern counties smashing whatever ‘monuments of idolatry and superstition’ he could find. Meticulous and uncompromising, Dowsing was one of the new breed: a yeoman recently self-styled as a gentleman, backed by a puritan community and parliamentarian leaders, well-versed in the <ORGANIZATION>Gospels</ORGANIZATION> but not a university graduate, and fiercely ready for action – a man rather like <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>, in fact.38

Institutions were collapsing, authority was dispersed, old certainties had been dashed. The <ORGANIZATION>Militia Ordinance</ORGANIZATION> arrogated to Parliament the right to legislate without royal assent; and the exclusion of bishops, impeachment of the Archbishop of <LOCATION>Canterbury</LOCATION> and dismantling of the church courts secularized ecclesiastical government. Hierarchy and obedience by no means disappeared, but initiative and imagination gained importance, especially at regional and local level. By commissioning Dowsing, the Earl of <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> had customized an official order (aimed solely at magistrates and churchwardens) into his own personal edict, thus allowing this obscure yeoman to become ‘Iconoclast General’.39 In these strange, turbulent days such things had become possible, even necessary if the holy war was to be won and a new order imposed. Besides, if the executive failed them, the Bible offered amateur reformers like Dowsing all the independent justification they needed.



<PERSON>William Dowsing</PERSON>, the ‘Iconoclast General’, whose tour of <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> in 1643–4 resembled the route taken by the witchfinders a couple of years later

A budding witchfinder could trace his call to arms to the same source. Many biblical texts condemning religious images also contained injunctions against witchcraft; like idols, witches dishonoured God and disobeyed the cardinal command that He alone be worshipped. It had long been conventional for sermons and treatises against witchcraft to cite Exodus 22:18, ‘Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live’; but less well known was the prohibition of sacrificial offerings which followed that text. Similar rules were set down in <LOCATION>Deuteronomy</LOCATION>; and in Chronicles could be found the story of <LOCATION>Manesseh</LOCATION>, ruler of <LOCATION>Jerusalem</LOCATION>, who not only ‘set a carved image, the idol which he had made, in the house of God’, but ‘used witchcraft, and dealt with a familiar spirit’.40 Then there was <PERSON>Micah</PERSON> 5:12–13: ‘And I will cut off witchcrafts out of thine hand; and thou shalt have no more soothsayers. Thy graven images also will I cut off, and thy standing images out of the midst of thee.’ And finally, the Book of Revelation predicted that into the fiery lake would go not just murderers, whoremongers and liars, but ‘sorcerers and idolators’. No surprise, then, that many East Anglian activists came to regard witches as they did devotional art: as yet another symbol of idolatry and evil to be rooted out and destroyed.41





2


Strange Effects




AS LAWYER’S CLERK, entrepreneur or man of leisure, in the early 1640s <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> moved to <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>, nine miles across the <LOCATION>Stour</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Great Wenham</LOCATION>. Now in his early twenties, he had come into his inheritance, enough to enable him to take a house and establish himself as a gentleman. According to later tradition, he lived on <LOCATION>South Street</LOCATION> and bought the Thorn Inn at <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>. Before long he had begun to worry about witches. He may already have been acquainted with the theory from works like <PERSON>James</PERSON> I’s <PERSON>Daemonologie</PERSON>, and A Guide to Grand-Jury Men by clergyman <PERSON>Richard Bernard</PERSON>; but real events put flesh on the bones. Newcomers to any town became familiar with the memories and myths that rooted the community in space and time. Sad and mysterious incidents were linked to landscape and landmarks: barren ground where a murdered corpse was found, a creaking tree from which a man had hanged himself, a stone scarred with the claw-marks of the devil. People recalled storms and floods, eclipses and meteors, plagues and monstrous births, visions and visitations. And they remembered witches, a legacy the families of the accused were never allowed to forget. Memory, like witchery, ran in the blood.1

In 1644 the crime of witchcraft was a century old in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, and during that century the county of <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION> had staged more trials than any other. <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON>’s original Act of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> had barely been used before its repeal in a legislative overhaul, then <PERSON>Edward VI</PERSON> died before it could be replaced.2 His Roman Catholic successor <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> showed little interest in witches, but when <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> became queen in 1558, senior <ORGANIZATION>Protestant</ORGANIZATION> clerics came back from their <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> exile concerned about the dangers of sorcery.3 The threat of <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> I’s Catholic enemies was often conflated with the witch-menace, while word from the provinces indicated that fear of witches (defined as apostates as well as murderers) was escalating. In the early 1560s ecclesiastical courts in the diocese of <LOCATION>Canterbury</LOCATION>, not far from <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION>, were no longer hearing just minor accusations of incantation and magical healing, but cases of full-blown maleficium – that is, those in which livestock and other property were alleged to have been destroyed, or people killed and injured. Since it was inappropriate for the <ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION> to be trying capital crimes, a new statute was passed in 1563.4

In the implementation of the Witchcraft Act, <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION> led the way. The first execution occurred there in 1564, followed two years later by a multiple trial reported in a cheap pamphlet; by 1581 there had been another eight significant outbreaks. In that year, anxiety at <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION> led to the passing of a statute forbidding magical forecasts of the queen’s death.5 A few months later at least ten women from <LOCATION>St Osyth</LOCATION>, a town with strong Catholic traditions, were tried as witches, and an account also went into print. Indictments for witchcraft were filed at the <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION> assizes throughout the last two decades of the sixteenth century, amounting to more than two hundred in all. Although as few as one in six of those indicted were executed, no Elizabethan man, woman or child a day’s ride from <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION> need have missed the excitement of a witch-hanging at some point in their lives. Executions were popular with all social ranks and degrees, and for those unable to travel to the assizes, eyewitness accounts were spread by word of mouth and the broadsides and books sold by itinerant pedlars. With every year the black inventory of witches grew longer in folklore.6

By the time the crown passed to <PERSON>James VI</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION> was the English shire that had best squared up to the devil, having tried 180 suspects. Almost all had been charged with attacking persons and property, however, rather than compacting with evil spirits. Just as it had been thought inappropriate for maleficium to be tried by the ecclesiastical authorities, so the invocation of demons had been considered an unfit matter for secular law, but by 1600 attitudes were changing.7 Elizabethan thinking on the subject, mostly among Protestant clerics, had raised the status of witchcraft from a part of the squabbles and suspicions of rural society into the ultimate spiritual crime. The effect of this was felt in everyday life, notably in a proliferation of cases of alleged diabolic possession. And yet the twist given to witchcraft accusations by an increasing number of adolescent girls blaming old women for their frenzies was less significant than the ensuing propaganda war between evangelical puritans and their Catholic opponents. Each side laid claim to a unique efficacy in dispossession, identifying this gift as a divine imprimatur. For a monarch and episcopate trying to steer a middle way for the Church, these claims were tiresome and dangerous. It was necessary for the state to punish witches; it was vital that it should restrain wanton exorcists.



Witches hanged at <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION> in 1589. A toad copulates with a ferret, a sign that they are diabolic spirits; another comes to suckle the witch, who cups her breast in anticipation

In 1604, the year after <PERSON>James</PERSON> succeeded <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>, new Church canons forbade unlicensed exorcism, and a revised Witchcraft Act made the conjuration of spirits a capital crime.8 At a stroke, genuine cases of possession – those that were not palpably fraudulent – were taken away from the firebrand exorcists and placed under the jurisdiction of the courts. The enduring image of the king as a slobbering bon viveur of dubious sexuality almost invariably embraces witch-hunting as well. As King of <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> he had helped to interrogate witches in <LOCATION>North Berwick</LOCATION>, and in 1597 had written a learned tract, <PERSON>Daemonologie</PERSON>. Small wonder that when this was republished in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in 1603, it became required reading not just for clergymen but for anyone interested in the mind of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>’s new monarch; naturally this included the gentry from whom the magistracy was drawn. According to <PERSON>James</PERSON>, the devil was a tangible force of evil, waging war on mankind in its last age. Although simple folk exaggerated the effectiveness of diabolic power, he argued, witches were none the less vermin to be exterminated, because they had switched their allegiance from God to Satan. For all its philosophical subtlety, <PERSON>Daemonologie</PERSON> was both an academic manifesto in favour of witch-hunting, and a practical manual for the job.9



King <PERSON>James</PERSON> interrogates the <LOCATION>North Berwick</LOCATION> witches, c. 1591

Yet no sooner had the king thrown down the gauntlet than his policy of restraining religious extremists necessitated a change of tack. The Archbishop of Canterbury <PERSON>Richard Bancroft</PERSON>, appointed in 1604, had declared war on militant Calvinists (for whom a belief in possession was a shibboleth), and <PERSON>James</PERSON> backed him; Jesuit exorcists would also be made to conform. In private the king adhered to his ideas about witches; in public he was now far more sceptical. Not only did he order investigations – in 1611, for instance, one ‘to search out the truth of a supposed witchcrafte Comitted upon six young maydes’ – but he delighted in exposing fraud at first hand.10 By the time <PERSON>Daemonologie</PERSON> was republished in 1616, <PERSON>James</PERSON> was more passionate about deer-hunting than ever he had been about witch-hunting. In that year he castigated a pair of judges for executing nine witches at <LOCATION>Leicester</LOCATION>, an intervention with profound consequences in an age when ambitious men kept an ear cocked to catch every royal hint. Only a judge without a care for his future career would have ignored this one; executions abated.11

More cases of imposture came to light in the early 1620s, such as that of <PERSON>Katherine Malpas</PERSON>, who claimed to have seen shape-shifting witches in her bedchamber. Drawing on countless stories in circulation, <PERSON>Malpas</PERSON> knew how to fake an accusation and attracted good audiences with her insane fits and Bible-hurling.12 Not all prosecutions failed because fraud was detected. <PERSON>Edward Jorden</PERSON>’s Briefe Discourse of a Disease called the Suffocation of the Mother (1603), which attributed the hysteria of bewitchment to an affliction of the womb (or ‘mother’), promoted natural explanations for apparently supernatural illnesses. <PERSON>Jorden</PERSON> may have been the mouthpiece of the anti-puritan, anti-exorcist Archbishop <PERSON>Bancroft</PERSON>, but it was his effect upon the thinking of physicians that mattered.13 In 1622 <PERSON>Richard Napier</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Buckinghamshire</LOCATION> rector moonlighting as a healer, diagnosed ‘Epilepsie of the Mother’ in a girl locals believed to have a witchfinding spirit working through her. Using her voice, the spirit was alleged to have said ‘I have sent this Child to speake to shew all these wiches.’ <PERSON>Napier</PERSON> did not hesitate with his diagnosis: she was branded a hysteric.14 By the time <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> became king in 1625 witch-trials were highly likely to fail, for one or more of three reasons: exposure of the accuser as a fraud; insufficient evidence; or a natural medical explanation that chased witchcraft from the courtroom.

The witch-hunt that flared up in 1645 was therefore partly a reaction against the decline of prosecutions under <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> I, and partly a sign that witchfinding and the persecution of Catholics were linked in people’s minds. Under <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> anxiety about popish traitors had coincided with a high tide of witch-trials, so it was logical that the arrival of an anti-Calvinist king should have marked the ebb. Between 1625 and the start of the civil war, there were just twenty-seven trials at the <ORGANIZATION>Home Circuit</ORGANIZATION> assizes (covering <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Kent</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Surrey</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Sussex</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Hertfordshire</LOCATION>), and of the convictions that resulted only two were upheld.15 This was not to say that the population at large had forgotten about witchcraft; on the contrary, anxiety may have been increasing precisely because the law no longer seemed to offer protection. For all <PERSON>James</PERSON>’s exposures of fraudulence, most witchcraft accusations were not cynical plots cooked up to further private vendettas, but resulted from a sincere perception of danger.16

No words from on high could make people less scared of witches. Everyone knew that accusations might be malicious and that symptoms were easily faked; yet personal experiences of bewitchment were quite different. Fear of specific individuals was palpable, stemming from a widespread belief in the reality of witchcraft. Village life was full of ambiguity and aggression, suspicion and superstition. Most disputes were easily resolved, but if one party had a bad reputation, an unexplained misfortune occurring to another might be interpreted as the first blow of the second round. Magical or violent counter-measures might follow, failing those an arrest warrant from a magistrate. Such feelings were not confined to the lower orders. In the 1620s the children of the <LOCATION>Yorkshire</LOCATION> poet <PERSON>Edward Fairfax</PERSON> were troubled by visions, leading to a series of arrests. The suspected women were initially discharged, then retried at <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>’s insistence. This time the cautious judge advised the jury that the case had ‘reached not to the point of the statute’, and so despite the plaintiff’s status the suspects were acquitted.17 Like many who had been poorly served by the law, <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> was bemused, observing that many people doubted his judgement ‘for they thincke th[a]t there be noe Witches at all’. He disagreed, warning that ‘I hear & fear there be many’.18

The pattern was fixed for a decade: Crown and Church opposing puritans and their demonology; anxiety about witches unchecked by the courts; and widening divisions over religion, taxation, land and authority. By 1640, as <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> I fought Calvinists in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> and tussled with a reconvened <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Westminster</ORGANIZATION>, the tide was turning again. As the political crisis deepened, so popular fears resurfaced.19 Clients of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>’s most famous astrologer <PERSON>William Lilly</PERSON> – inveterate worriers about illnesses, journeys, lawsuits, missing persons and lost property – now seemed more anxiety-ridden than ever.20 In 1642 every English person was thrown into times which, in <ORGANIZATION>Lilly</ORGANIZATION>’s own words, were ‘very troublesome and expensive, when warr and the souldier comand, and faction and division both in <ORGANIZATION>Church & Comonwealth</ORGANIZATION>, do aboundantly afflict us’.21 Once again, the dangers of witchcraft were voiced with confidence in public. In March 1645 nowhere was this more true than at <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>, where the tailor <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON>’s wife lay sick.

The Manningtree known to <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> was a small but prosperous market town on the northern edge of the Tendring Hundred, a dense maze of marsh, wood and farmland. A riverside path led to the port of <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>, by tradition a place where mistletoe grew, and where the eldest residents remembered waving ships off to fight the Spanish Armada. The harbour with its warehouses and jetties overlooked the mile-wide estuary of the <LOCATION>Stour</LOCATION> where at high tide ships would dock and depart, taking grain to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and returning with manure. When the tide went out activity subsided and sea birds picked over the mudflats. Across the water, mists permitting, <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON> could have seen the <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> villages of <LOCATION>Brantham</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Stutton</LOCATION>: chimney smoke by day, and at twilight candles in the windows. Manningtree itself occupied just twenty-two acres, its narrow lanes packed with the homes of weavers, brewers, artisans and tradesmen. At the central crossroads, where the high street met the road to the south, stood the market-place with its assembly room and clock tower. At <LOCATION>Whitsun</LOCATION> a fair attracted many visitors who drank <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> ale and feasted on the roast ox to which <PERSON>Shakespeare</PERSON> had referred. At the fringes, where the bounds of the township gave way to fields, were scattered the shacks and tumbledown cottages of the poor: the labourers, dockers and beggars, the decrepit and the dispossessed.22

At the Reformation the ecclesiastical manors of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION> had passed to Sir <PERSON>John Rainsforth</PERSON>, but by the time <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> arrived several families had come to dominate as landowners, magistrates, manufacturers and merchants. Dynasties old and new left monuments in the churches of <ORGANIZATION>St Mary</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Mistley Heath</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>St Michael</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>. A generation earlier Manningtree folk had been forced to walk the mile to <ORGANIZATION>St Mary</ORGANIZATION>’s, their own church having burnt down; but complaints about the town’s vulnerability to pirates while its people were at prayer led to the building of a chapel of ease in 1616. The roof timbers came from old ships, a mixture of the spiritual and the mercantile representative of its congregation. Traditions were solidly Protestant and, by the 1640s, Presbyterian. In the reign of Queen <PERSON>Mary</PERSON> townsmen had tried to stop a man being burned for refusing to attend Mass, but had been restrained by <PERSON>Bishop Bonner</PERSON>’s guards. The martyr’s memory never faded. Reactions to a visit in 1633 by another hated prelate, Bishop <PERSON>William Laud</PERSON>, were not recorded, but it is easy to imagine what local people muttered under their breath. Laud generously gave <ORGANIZATION>St Michael</ORGANIZATION>’s four pieces of communion plate bearing his coat of arms, but from the time he was made Archbishop of <LOCATION>Canterbury</LOCATION> that year, in the eyes of the godly his influence was entirely negative.23

To a Manningtree puritan of the 1640s Laud’s legacy may not have been actually evil, but it was certainly scandalous – a word used throughout <ORGANIZATION>Essex</ORGANIZATION> whenever criticism of the clergy was voiced. From the parish of Stisted, for example, came news that the minister, <PERSON>Christopher Newsted</PERSON>, was a base Arminian who incited opposition to <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and denied the <ORGANIZATION>Solemn League</ORGANIZATION> and Covenant. Introduced in 1643, this was a popular pledge to replace episcopal hierarchy with local Presbyterian church government; but, like the Protestation Oath, from 1641 sworn by thousands of men and women ‘against all popery and popish innovation’, it became an oath of allegiance to <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> – a semi-sacred ritual to distinguish friend from foe, <PERSON>Christ</PERSON> from <PERSON>Antichrist</PERSON>.24 By the outbreak of war, the godly camp saw its enemy as a many-headed monster breaching every political, religious and moral code. At <LOCATION>Stisted</LOCATION>, not only did the parishioners have <PERSON>Christopher Newsted</PERSON> removed by the <ORGANIZATION>Committee for Scandalous Ministers</ORGANIZATION> but rumours spread that the local gentry hosted orgies at which spirits were invoked by a black-suited sorcerer. Scandal first flirted with evil, then went the whole way with accusations of demon worship. In this climate, the number of witches presented for trial in <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION> began to creep upwards.25



A godly minister and his parishioners take the Protestation Oath against popery

In 1638 four women were sent to <LOCATION>Colchester</LOCATION> prison by a magistrate named Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON>, a gentleman who lived at <LOCATION>Bradfield Hall</LOCATION>, just outside <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>. All were from the Tendring Hundred, where <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> held manors in <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kirby</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lawford</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Tendring</PERSON> itself.26 Despite being in his mid seventies <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> still toured his estates, although at that time almost certainly in a carriage. Knighted early in the reign of <PERSON>James</PERSON> I and made a baronet in 1611, he had married into a respectable family from <LOCATION>Lavenham</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> and in 1614 was elected sheriff of <LOCATION>Essex</LOCATION> and MP for <LOCATION>Harwich</LOCATION>. In the 1620s he represented his county in <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and resisted <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> I’s forced loan, for which he was imprisoned. <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON>’s dissent in the matter of royal finance was reinforced by his puritanism. He sent his three sons to the godly seminary, <ORGANIZATION>Emmanuel College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, from which his middle son and namesake emerged as a committed Presbyterian with his sights set on the law and government; in <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> in 1640 he denounced Archbishop Laud as ‘the sty of all pestilential filth that hath infested the state and government of this commonwealth’. Alongside his religious values, Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON> taught his sons not to flinch from using the law to suppress evil. Without him, <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>’ mission might never have got off the ground.27

Almost all the suspicions that lay behind the witchcraft accusations of March 1645 originated in Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON>’s jurisdiction, mostly on his estates. In 1640 a woman named <PERSON>Sarah Hatyn</PERSON> was said to have threatened the constable of <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Francis Stock</PERSON>, after he pressed her husband to serve as a soldier. Soon afterwards Stock’s wife reported having seen a snake in the house; she believed it to be a diabolical imp, and when she tried to kill it with a spade, it vanished. Within a few days, Goodwife Stock and two of her children were dead. In the following year Stock’s servant fell sick after striking <PERSON>Sarah Hatyn</PERSON>’s son, and swore on his death-bed that she had bewitched him. In 1642 <PERSON>Hatyn</PERSON> found herself in the frame for yet another mysterious murder.28

Since then, two widows named <PERSON>Elizabeth Harvey</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marian Hocket</PERSON> had also fallen under suspicion, but the people of <PERSON>Ramsey</PERSON> lacked the will or the courage to initiate a prosecution, doubtless aware of how few had been successful in recent years. Meanwhile, at <LOCATION>Thorpele-Soken</LOCATION>, a few miles to the south, <PERSON>Margaret Moone</PERSON> was accused of bewitching the <PERSON>Rawbood</PERSON> family, occupants of a house from which she had been evicted. In 1640 <PERSON>Moone</PERSON> was thought to have murdered the baby daughter of an influential farmer, and three years later to have destroyed another man’s cow. For all four women, time was short.29

In Manningtree the evil spread to <PERSON>Richard Edwards</PERSON>, a figure well connected to Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON> in religion and administration. One of the largest landowners in <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Lawford</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> was easily the richest man in the town, and had been made chief constable of the Tendring Hundred in 1642. He was thus a formidable enemy. In the summer of 1644 two of his cattle died as they were being driven past a witch’s house in <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>; the insides of the carcasses bore no signs of disease. Worse followed. <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>’ newborn son was placed in the charge of a <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> wet-nurse who lived close to the prime suspect, <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>. Before long the baby fell into ‘very strange fits, extending the limbs, and rowling the eyes’, and within a few days had died.30

<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> knew he was not the only one under attack. <PERSON>Sarah Bright</PERSON> stood accused of having killed the child of a prosperous stonemason, and <PERSON>Robert Tayler</PERSON>, another well-heeled citizen and leading Presbyterian, suspected a ‘lewd woman’ named <PERSON>Elizabeth Gooding</PERSON> of having bewitched his horse.31 Some trials had already taken place at <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION> by then, including those of two of the women committed by Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON> in 1638; the case of a labourer’s wife from <ORGANIZATION>Hatfield Broad Oak</ORGANIZATION> had also been heard. Another woman was imprisoned at <LOCATION>Colchester</LOCATION> and charged. Like <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON>, <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> owned an estate in <LOCATION>Ramsey</LOCATION>, where whispering about witchcraft was rife. At a time when prominent gentry were warning magistrates that the county was being flooded with Catholics and other enemies of the state, it began to seem as though a conspiratorial network of popish and diabolical traitors spread across the Tendring Hundred.32

Concern also focused on the parish of <PERSON>Lawford</PERSON>. <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> and her daughter <PERSON>Rebecca</PERSON> had migrated from <LOCATION>Rivenhall</LOCATION> in 1638, and were said to have adopted pious manners to conceal a reputation for witchcraft.33 But word had spread. In their second year at <PERSON>Lawford John Cutler</PERSON>, a prominent yeoman, blamed <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> for his son’s death, and although he did not prosecute her, in 1641 his neighbour <PERSON>Thomas Hart</PERSON> did, for causing the death of a sow. <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> was tried that spring and acquitted; but at the following assizes a petition branding her ‘a very dangerous p[er]son amongest her neighbours’ was presented to the judges, who instructed local magistrate Sir <PERSON>Thomas Bowes</PERSON> to arrange for her to be prosecuted. She was unable to raise the bail money, so <PERSON>Bowes</PERSON> had her arrested and carted the eight miles back to <LOCATION>Colchester</LOCATION>, and from there, in March 1642, to the assizes at <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION>. Again she escaped punishment. But the magistrate, who lived at <LOCATION>Great Bromley Hall</LOCATION>, seven miles south of <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION>, was, like <PERSON>Robert Tayler</PERSON>, a man in his prime and an enthusiastic Presbyterian, and now his interest was aroused. Another leading Presbyterian in the region was <PERSON>George Francis</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Rivenhall</LOCATION>, a principal inhabitant of his parish whose child had died mysteriously when the Wests lived there.34 Hostility was growing, to witches in general and to <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> in particular.

<PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>’ claim to have been menaced by witches in 1644 was just one strand in a web of conflict, suspicion and godly conviction. The beliefs of <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON> were another. Older than <PERSON>Hopkins</PERSON>, in his mid thirties, <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> had like him grown up in rural <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, and may also have shared his <LOCATION>Cambridgeshire</LOCATION> ancestry.35 At <LOCATION>Long Melford</LOCATION>, possibly his birthplace, he met and married <PERSON>Agnes Cawston</PERSON>, and together they set up home in <LOCATION>Lawshall</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Bury St Edmunds</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Agnes</PERSON>’s mother had moved after her own remarriage.36 <PERSON>John</PERSON> and <PERSON>Agnes</PERSON>’s first child, a girl, was baptized there early in 1644.37 The pride of the parish was the church of All Saints, rebuilt in the fifteenth century with profits from the cloth industry and now a powerhouse of Protestant preaching. Reform had spread quickly in <LOCATION>Lawshall</LOCATION>, and by 1600 the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic</ORGANIZATION> community had been driven to practise their religion in secret, at <LOCATION>Coldham Hall</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> himself was a staunch puritan, with a censorious manner and a mind steeped in Scripture. What he was doing in <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> in 1645 is not known, but since he maintained a house there he was presumably engaged in business of some sort.

<PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> was a man after <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON>’ heart, and each saw a future in collaboration with the other. As well as similar geographical origins, the two men shared a gentility that originated more in self-assertion than in wealth, estate, breeding, or title. Like many puritans of their age they chose to define themselves according to the present, not the past, not only in the matter of their gentility but specifically with regard to their predestined election to the sainthood, an unswerving duty to God, and a heartfelt calling to serve the commonwealth. Above all, they were men of action.

The first weeks of 1645 offered little hope of peace. Division, it seemed, bred only more division. The Earl of <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> had parted company with <PERSON>Oliver Cromwell</PERSON>, second-in-command of the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Association Army</ORGANIZATION>, after a disagreement about the conduct of the war; and in <ORGANIZATION>Parliament Cromwell</ORGANIZATION>’s Independents, who opposed a national Church on the old model, were a thorn in the side of the Presbyterian majority. The last major battle had been indecisive, and in February peace talks ended in disarray. In frosty streets and markets people talked of stalemate and despair, as if both war and winter would last forever. Public anxiety reached new heights. The astrologer <PERSON>William Lilly</PERSON> was inundated with clients, and recorded their special concerns in his notebooks: which side to support; whether particular soldiers were alive; and, if so, the date when they would come home.38

Early in January <PERSON>Lilly</PERSON> was asked to predict how and when Archbishop Laud would die. He deliberated over his answer and was overtaken by events: Laud was beheaded on the 10th. Though he had been despised by many in life, his violent death on <PERSON>Tower Hill</PERSON> was nevertheless seen as another sign that the ordered world was coming apart at the seams. Some of <PERSON>Lilly</PERSON>’s clients, both rich and poor, reflected this public alarm in a private belief that they were possessed or bewitched.39 Rumours circulated that Major-General <PERSON>Cromwell</PERSON> looked to Satan for military power, when what he really needed was better leadership and organization.40 To this end, <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> replaced the <ORGANIZATION>Earl of Essex</ORGANIZATION> as commander-in-chief with the youthful, dashing Sir <PERSON>Thomas Fairfax</PERSON>, and plans were approved to recruit and train a <ORGANIZATION>New Model Army</ORGANIZATION>: a tough, ruthless killing machine run on discipline and godliness. Some of the worst fighting lay ahead. Early in March 1645 <PERSON>Lilly</PERSON> calculated what he called ‘An Astrologicall judgment upon the Sunn’, a horoscope for the year to come, which, he said, would be thick with ‘many hott skirmishes [and] much bloodshead in those unseasonable tymes of the yeare’. Men’s minds, he warned grimly, would be corrupted by the planets, causing their conduct to be ‘rapacious, cruell, treacherous’.41

At <LOCATION>Lawford</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Thomas Hart</PERSON> and his wife Prudence were preoccupied with the punishment of <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON>. In 1641 their pursuit of <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in the courts had ended in acquittal, which meant that she had returned home bearing an extra grudge against them. They waited nervously, not knowing where or when the next blow would fall. Meanwhile <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON>’s daughter <PERSON>Rebecca</PERSON> had started giving <PERSON>Prudence Hart</PERSON> that familiar spiteful look: a wounding power believed to flow from the eyes of envious women. In the summer of 1644 Goodwife <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> became pregnant, and fared well through the autumn and winter. But one Sunday towards the end of February 1645, a severe abdominal pain forced her to leave the church. Before she could get home, she collapsed in the street and gave birth prematurely to a stillborn child.42

Again and again the memory of her dead child and a craving for vengeance against the <ORGANIZATION>Wests</ORGANIZATION> coursed round <PERSON>Prudence Hart</PERSON>’s brain until a terrifying experience overwhelmed her:

… being in her bed, in the night, something fell down upon her right side, but being dark, she cannot tell in what shape it was: And that presently shee was taken lame on that side, with extraordinary pains and burning, but recovered again within a few dayes after. And … she verily believeth, that <PERSON>Rebecca West</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> her mother, were the cause of her pains … because the said <PERSON>Rebecca West</PERSON> ever thought this Informant to be her greatest enemy.

The rector of <PERSON>Lawford</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Edes</PERSON>, was a Presbyterian respected in the community for thirty years, and well connected to ministers throughout the Tendring Hundred and <LOCATION>Dedham Vale</LOCATION>. He had seen <PERSON>Prudence Hart</PERSON> stagger from the church that day, and he knew what she had suffered at the hands of <PERSON>Anne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rebecca West</PERSON>. He vowed to help if he could. At the beginning of March 1645 the collective will to punish the <ORGANIZATION>Wests</ORGANIZATION> was given an additional boost when yeoman <PERSON>John Cutler</PERSON>, who believed <PERSON>Anne West</PERSON> had killed his son five years earlier, pledged to back both <PERSON>Thomas Hart</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Edes</PERSON> if they took legal action.43

Events a mile away at <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> provided the final encouragement. By now the town was a tinder-box of grief, wrath and excitement, just waiting for a spark. Gossip about witchcraft was rife, including the allegations made by <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON> against <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>, and people looked to their leaders for deliverance. Unable to contain their frustration, some townsmen confronted Widow <PERSON>Clarke</PERSON>, and were shocked and gratified to hear her admit an association with several witches, although she declined to name them. Her faltering confession was compressed into coherent prose and entrusted to <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON>, who was known to have the ear of Sir <PERSON>Harbottle Grimston</PERSON> and Sir <PERSON>Thomas Bowes</PERSON>. The lord of the manor had died in 1638, and the town’s rector <PERSON>Thomas Witham</PERSON> had left for <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in 1643 and since died himself. In the absence of any powerful seigneurial or clerical influence in <LOCATION>Manningtree</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mistley</LOCATION>, personal connections of the sort <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> had nurtured with the magistrates had come to acquire great political significance.44

It was Friday 21 March 1645, a day when the magistrates made themselves available to hear complaints about sin, crime and disorder, probably at the assembly room in the market-place. The elderly <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> and his younger colleague – Bowes was around forty – settled themselves, and the necessary papers and reference works were arranged on the table.45 A clerk sat in attendance, inkpot filled, quills cut to his liking. <PERSON>John Stearne</PERSON> was announced, and was shown into the room. At the request of the townsmen, he told the magistrates, he had brought a transcript of <PERSON>Clarke</PERSON>’s confession for their consideration. <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bowes</PERSON> discussed it a while, then, at the stroke of a pen, unwittingly initiated the most savage witch-hunt in English history: <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> departed holding what he later described as a ‘warrant … for the searching of such persons as I should nominate’.46 It had been agreed that before going any further, <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON> was to discover from <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON> the names of the other witches. <PERSON>Matthew Hopkins</PERSON> volunteered to assist him, and together they discussed how best to proceed. <PERSON>Stearne</PERSON>, particularly, was all for seeing whether the old woman would float in water – the swimming test once favoured by <PERSON>James</PERSON> I – but it is likely that the magistrates forbade this as a dubious and sinful ordeal.47

<PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> and Bowes were not completely above making concessions to superstition, however. Eager to testify against <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Rivet</PERSON> presented himself to them that same Friday. The fact that he had incited a cunning woman to commit an illegal act of sorcery the magistrates overlooked, in view of the gravity of the situation. <PERSON>Grimston</PERSON> was the kind of godly man who counselled a patient acceptance of the workings of providence, advising with regard to diseases that, ‘be they never so grievous and continuall, thou oughtest to kisse these rods as love tokens received from the Almightie’.48 But he and <PERSON>Bowes</PERSON> were also instruments of God’s law, and justice had to be done. They ordered that <PERSON>Elizabeth Clarke</PERSON> be arrested and her body searched by four honest and experienced women for signs that she had suckled evil spirits. After this, she was to be watched for three nights to see whether her imps came for sustenance.